<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two discourses concerning the divinity of Our Saviour whereunto are added some articles subscribed by all the French divines in or about London, in opposition to the Socinians / translated out of French.</title>
            <author>La Mothe, Claude Grostête, sieur de, 1647-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49137</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14659</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12157899</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12157899</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55198</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49137)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55198)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 604:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two discourses concerning the divinity of Our Saviour whereunto are added some articles subscribed by all the French divines in or about London, in opposition to the Socinians / translated out of French.</title>
                  <author>La Mothe, Claude Grostête, sieur de, 1647-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 64, 57-60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Divinity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55198:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO DISCOURSES Concerning the DIVINITY OF OUR SAVIOUR.</p>
            <p>Whereunto are added ſome Articles ſubſcribed by all the <hi>French</hi> Divines in or about <hi>London,</hi> in Oppoſition to the SOCINIANS.<hi>Tranſlated out of</hi> French.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>March 22. 1692/3.</date>
                           </dateline> 
                           <signed>Guil. Lancaſter.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:55198:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55198:2"/>
            <head>To His Grace, the Duke of <hi>Sconberg,</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Harwich,</hi> Earl of <hi>Brantford,</hi> Baron of <hi>Tays,</hi> Count of the <hi>Holy Empire,</hi> Lieutenant-General of His Majeſty's Army, and Colonel of the Firſt Regiment of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Guards.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DID the Fate of Books depend upon the Quality of the Perſons to whom they are Dedicated, I ſhould be very ſecure, that the two following Diſcourſes would be kindly received, becauſe I have preſum'd to put 'em under the Protection of one of the Greateſt Perſons that can be made choice of. It is very well known, My Lord, that Your Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Family has a long Succeſſion of Anceſtors, whoſe Blood has been mixt with that of divers Princes; and it is not long ago ſince we loſt the Duke your Father, in whoſe Air we ſaw all the Traces of ſo Auguſt a Pedigree. He maintain'd the Glory of His Birth, by all the Merit neceſſary to make a Hero. So prudent in his Conduct, that he never took a falſe Meaſure; Indefatigably Vigilant, Valiant, and Couragious in Action; theſe Great Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties being joined to a Goodneſs, that made Acceſs to him always eaſy; and a Piety that gave Example to our whole Church, could not but render him the Object of our Admiration. I know, My Lord, there is no need of looking farther than Your own Grandeur, to find Matter for Your Praiſes: So the Liberty I have taken to ſpeak of the Duke Your Father, was only to gain an opportunity of drawing Your Picture without offence to Your Modeſty. I am not ignorant, that how great ſoever my Patron may be; yet the Publick, which judges of things as they are in themſelves, will not receive theſe Diſcourſes more favourably upon that account. But I have no farther deſign in the Choice, than to manifeſt the Obligations I have to Your Grace for Your Bounty, in affording me the Honour of Your Protection, and to aſſure You that I am with a profound reſpect,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Graces Moſt Humble and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient Servant and Chaplain, <hi>C. G. Lamothe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:55198:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>I Doubt not but ſome People will think it ſtrange, that I ſhould venture to Print any thing concerning the Divinity of our Saviour, when ſuch Excellent Sermons have been lately Publiſh'd upon the ſame Subject. This ſeems to be ſo ill tim'd, that I find my ſelf oblig'd to ſay ſomething in juſtification of my own Conduct. When I ſaw this Truth defended by the beſt Pens in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I thought it the Duty of the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters, who are Refugees there, to give ſome written proofs of the Conſtancy of their Faith in ſo important an Article. And this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of theirs cannot but carry ſome weight along with it; whether we reflect upon their great number; or conſider, that Religion was the Cauſe why they were Baniſhed from their own Countrey, It is indeed their Duty, as far as in them lyes, to Edifie a Nation that has receiv'd them with a Charity becoming the Primitive Ages of the Church; and ſome proofs of their Conſtancy are likewiſe due to the Honour of their own Miniſtry. Several Ill-deſigning People have endeavour'd to caſt a Blemiſh upon them: Some have done it in <hi>France,</hi> with a deſign to make their Flocks, which now are gone aſtray, conceive an Averſion to their Ancient Paſtors; and others have thought by this means to gain Reputation to a Cauſe, which they themſelves are too much inclin'd to. When I ſaw that the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters in the clearing themſelves of this Reproach, were content to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct their Auditors in the True Faith by their Sermons only, whoſe Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects could not reach the Nation in which they have the Happineſs to live; I thought it my Duty to go farther, and that I ſhould not do a thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful to the Publick in Printing Two Diſcourſes upon this Subject; after having took Care that they ſhould be Examin'd by my Brethren, to the end it might appear, That the Doctrine I Teach, is that of our whole Body.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>We whoſe Names are under-written, being Appointed by the other <hi>French</hi> Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> have Read theſe Two Diſcourſes, and have found them entirely Conformable to the Word of God, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Doctrine of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants.
<list>
                     <item>Satur, <hi>Miniſter of the</hi> Savoy.</item>
                     <item>Graveral, <hi>Miniſter of the New</hi> French <hi>Church.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>The 8th. of</hi> March.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55198:3"/>
            <head>The Firſt Diſcourſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PHILIP. II. 6, 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Who being in the Form of God, thought it no Robbery to be equal with God: But made himfelf of no Reputation.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a very Judicious Obſervation which ſome Divines have made upon the Variety that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears throughout the whole Diſpenſation of the Goſpel. They have obſerv'd, that Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Meanneſs were ſo mix'd in it, that it ſeemed as if Providence had deſigned thereby to point out to us the two Natures of our Great Redeemer.</p>
            <p>From his very Conception we are entertained with the view of a God-Man; he was formed in the Womb of the poor Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> this ſpeaks him Man: But the Holy Ghoſt preſides at his Conception; this ſhews him to be more than Man. His Birth is proclaimed by Shepherds, but the Angels alſo bear a part in it. His Infancy is perſecuted by one King, but ador'd by three others. We find alſo, according to <hi>Origen</hi>'s Obſervation, that amongſt the Preſents which theſe Kings, or Wiſe-men offer'd to the Child Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, there was Myrth for the Mortal Man, and Incenſe for the Immortal God.</p>
            <p>The whole Life of our Saviour repreſents to us a like mixture: He undergoes a Temptation of Forty Days, but he hath Angels to miniſter unto him; he is hungry, but he curſeth the Fig-tree; he falls aſleep in the Ship, but he commands the Storm to a Calm: He weeps for his Friend <hi>Lazarus,</hi> but calls him out of his Grave
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55198:4"/>to life; he dies, but Nature ſeems to feel the Pangs of Death with him, and the Third Day he riſeth from the Dead. You ſee there runs a continued Parallel between the Humiliation of Man, and the Majeſty of God, in moſt of the Circumſtances of our Saviour's Life, that we may be aſſur'd of the Right which each of the two Natures hath to our belief of it.</p>
            <p>This Obſervation is ſtill more evident, from the Oppoſition St. <hi>Paul</hi> purpoſely makes between theſe two Natures, in ſeveral places. At the beginning of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> he ſpeaks of <hi>the Goſpel of God concerning his Son;</hi> here is the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt: but then, <hi>Who was made of the ſeed of David according to the fleſh;</hi> there is his Humanity. In the <hi>9th Chapter</hi> of the ſame <hi>Epiſtle</hi> he ſaith, That Chriſt came <hi>of the Father, according to the Fleſh;</hi> but that he is <hi>over all, God bleſſed for ever.</hi> In the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians</hi> it is ſaid, that <hi>God ſent his Son, made of a woman:</hi> Here we have the Son of God, and the Son of a Woman; and in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Timothy, God was manifeſt in the Fleſh.</hi> But there is no Paſſage where this Oppoſition is more diſtinctly ſet forth, than that which we have made choice of, on a day ſet aſide by the Church, for a Memorial of our Saviour's Humiliation; <hi>Who being in the Form of God,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, though it no Robbery to be equal with God: But made himſelf of no reputation;</hi> or Emptied himſelf, as the word in the Original ſignifies.</p>
            <p>The deſign of theſe words was to oblige the <hi>Philippians</hi> to Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Charity. There could be nothing of greater force to engage them to the practice of theſe two Vertues, than the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Jeſus Chriſt. They knew what paſs'd when our Saviour waſh'd his Diſciple's Feet: <hi>Ye call me Maſter and Lord, and ye ſay well, for ſo I am. If I then your Lord and Maſter have waſhed your feet, ye alſo ought to waſh one anothers feet: For I have given you an example, that ye ſhould do as I have done to you. Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, the ſervant is not greater than his Lord, &amp;c.</hi> This Principle being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conteſtably admitted by the <hi>Philippians,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> could not alledge a more preſſing Motive to eſtabliſh amongſt them a Spirit of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and Charity, than was that of the Example of our dear Lord, where both theſe Vertues appear with ſo much luſtre. <hi>Let therefore,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>this mind be in you, which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus, who being in the form of God, thought it no robbery to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual with God: yet he emptied himſelf, and took upon him the form of a Servant, and was made in the likeneſs of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:55198:4"/>
            <p>Theſe words furniſh us with two great Subjects for our Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Glory of the Eternal Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt, and his Emptying of himſelf in his Incarnation.</p>
            <p>In order to a thorough Explication of the words which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Divinity of our Saviour, we muſt firſt conſider the Literal Senſe, and then ſearch as far as the weakneſs of our Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will permit, into the Doctrine therein contain'd. The Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſenſe of theſe words preſents us with three Propoſitions: The Firſt is, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt was, before that he was made man.</hi> The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>That he was in the form of God, before ever he was in the form of man.</hi> The Third, <hi>That he thought it no robbery to be equal to his heavenly Father.</hi> Theſe are the Three Propoſitions <hi>St. Paul</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth here very clearly.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt was, before that he became Man: Who,</hi> ſaith <hi>St. Paul, being,</hi> or as it is in the Original <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in the form of God, did empty himſelf,</hi> or was made man. That which is not, cannot abaſe it ſelf, or become Man. A Truth which is proved at the very Propoſal of it.</p>
            <p>It would be hard to gueſs wherein the <hi>Soundneſs</hi> of <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Reaſoning did conſiſt, if Jeſus Chriſt had not exiſted before he was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> This way of arguing can have no Foundation but this; That Chriſt paſſed from one Condition to another; from a State of Glory, to a State of Abaſement, and in ſo doing hath ſet an Example, wherein a mixture of Humility and Charity invite, or rather force Chriſtians to an Imitation. A Doctrine truly worthy of <hi>St. Paul.</hi> But what ſenſe ſhall we make of it, if it be not true that our Saviour before his Birth of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin, was not in a more Glorious State than was that which he entred upon by his Nativity? Should we allow our ſelves to ſuppoſe, that Jeſus Chriſt began to exiſt by his Conception in the Womb of the Bleſſed Virgin? could we in this caſe be able to ſay, That he humble himſelf to that degree, as to be willing to be born after the manner of Men? Humility conſiſts in ſtepping down lower. Now that which is not, cannot deſcend, nor conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently humble it ſelf. He was therefore, before that he emptied himſelf by his Temporal Nativity.</p>
            <p>This is a Truth ſo clearly aſſerted in <hi>Scripture,</hi> that the oppoſite Error cannot be entertained by any, but thoſe who either openly or ſecretly reject the Authority of that Divine Book. I will not go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55198:5"/>to quote all the Paſſages we find there, to prove the Pre-exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence of our Bleſſed Saviour; the number of them is ſo great, that it would take up too much of our time. Nevertheleſs, for confirmation of the Propoſition we are about, we ſhall put you in mind, that Jeſus Chriſt himſelf declares, that he was come down from Heaven, and that he was in Heaven before ever he aſcended thither. This Pre-exiſtence will appear very evidently, by a Set of gradual Proofs drawn from the Scriptures concerning it.</p>
            <p>Our Bleſſed Saviour was before <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> tho he, as his Forerunner, was born before him. Hear we the Depoſition of this Illuſtrious Witneſs;<note place="margin">John 1.30.</note> 
               <hi>This is he of whom I ſaid, After me cometh a man who is preferred before me, for he was before me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, what is more, our Saviour was in <hi>Moſes</hi> his time, who was ſo many Ages before <hi>John the Baptiſt;</hi> for is it not ſaid, That the <hi>Iſralites,</hi> contemporary with that great Law giver, did tempt Chriſt? <hi>Neither let us tempt Chriſt,</hi> ſaith our Apoſtle, <hi>as ſome of them alſo tempted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>and were deſtroyed of Serpents.</hi> When <hi>Moſes</hi> refuſed to be called the Son of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daughter, and forſook the Court of <hi>Aegypt</hi> to follow the Divine Call, the Author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> informs us,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> that in ſo doing, <hi>he preferr'd the reproach of Chriſt before the treaſures of Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us go further ſtill, and we ſhall find, that our Bleſſed Lord was before <hi>Abraham;</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 8.58.</note> 
               <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, Before Abraham was, I am.</hi> This was a very emphatical Teſtimony to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who look'd upon this Patriarch as the firſt Stock of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Let us go back as far as <hi>Noah,</hi> and we ſhall find, that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was at that time alſo, according to the Teſtimony of <hi>St. Peter;</hi> who tells us, That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt preached to the ſpirits that were diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in the time of Noah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 3.19.</note> So long ſince, Jeſus Chriſt took care of Sinners.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt we ſtop here; for if we look back to the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World,<note place="margin">John 1.1. Col. 1.17.</note> we ſhall find our Saviour <hi>aſſiſting</hi> there. <hi>In the beginning was the word. He is before all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, how could it be otherwiſe, but that he muſt have been at the beginning of the world, ſince the world ows its Creation to him? <hi>Without him was not any thing made, that was made. I was brought forth when yet there were no depths,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 1.3 Prov. 8.24, 25:</note> 
               <hi>nor fountains abounding with water. Before the Mountains were ſetled, before the hills, was I brought forth.</hi> As the Wiſe King introduceth our Saviour ſpeaking in the 8th Chapter of the <hi>Proverbs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55198:5"/>
            <p>Neither muſt we conclude from all theſe Expreſſions, that the Exiſtence of our Saviour did only precede the Creation of the World for a little time: for to be before the World, before the ſetling of the Mountains; to be in the Beginning, to be the <hi>Alpha</hi> of all things, are Expreſſions the Scripture makes uſe of to ſignifie Eternity.</p>
            <p>The Ground of this manner of ſpeaking is very ſolid; for the Holy Spirit in his Applications to men, makes uſe of ſuch Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as they underſtand. Now when the Queſtion is about time, it is neceſſary that they who would be underſtood, ſhould repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to our Imagination ſome created Object, to meaſure its Dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by. Our Imagination cannot frame any thing to it ſelf before the Creation of the World: Whatſoever is beyond, that is a dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſwallows up and confounds our Apprehenſion. Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is an Abyſs to our Finite Capacity: Wherefore the Holy Ghoſt being willing to repreſent to our Minds the Duration of that which is without beginning, contents himſelf ſimply to declare, That it was before the beginning of the World. It is not in favour of the Eternity of our Bleſſed Saviour that we ſpeak thus, becauſe we know that the Eternity of the Divine Nature hath in ſome ſort been limited by a like Phraſe. Doth not the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> expreſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thus; <hi>Before the mountains were brought forth, or ever thou hadſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the earth, and the world, even from everlaſting, to everlaſting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.2.</note> 
               <hi>thou art God.</hi> To take the Senſe of the Scriptures, let us ſay, That our Bleſſed Saviour hath ever been. This is the Firſt Propoſition; Our Saviour was, before he was man.</p>
            <p>The Second Propoſition is; That our Saviour was in the Form of God, before ever he was in the Form of a Servant; before that he was Man, he was in the Form of God. It was not therefore by his miraculous Conception; it was not by the power he had to do Miracles; it was not by his Glorious Reſurrection; it was not by his Elevation to that Supereminent Dignity he poſſeſſeth in the Church, that he was made the Son of God, as the Enemies of his Glory would perſwade us: No, he was God before that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe things came to paſs; he was in the Form of God before ever he ſtooped to take upon him the Form of a Man. You ſpeak to us of a Glory, whereof the Humanity of our Bleſſed Lord was, as it were, the Foundation and Riſe: whereas <hi>St. Paul</hi> here enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains us with the Glory he was poſſeſs'd of before his becoming
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55198:6"/>Man: he was like to God before ever he was made like to Men. Let us keep cloſe to the Phraſe of the Apoſtle; <hi>Who being in the form of God, emptied himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Second Propoſtion ſupports and confirms the Frſt, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently proving, that our Lord was, before his being Man; yea, and that he was from all Eternity; for without this he could not have been in the Form of God. That which is born in time, bears no Reſemblance with that which is Eternal; Finite and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite are oppoſite to one another. If Jeſus Chriſt had began to be from his Conception in the Womb of the Bleſſed Virgin: let us go farther; if his Beginning had only been contemporary with that of the World, it could not have been ſaid of him, That he was in the Form of God; his Duration, at the moſt, would but have been of Six Thouſand Years; and what is that to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? A Point bears more proportion to the Univerſe, and one Drop of Water to the Ocean. Was there a Being that had exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted a Million of Years before the World, that Being would ſtill be at an infinite diſtance from Eternity; neither ſhould we be able to ſay, though we ſhould ſuppoſe nothing to be wanting in it but Time, that it was like the Deity. In a word, had not our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our been Eternal, he could not be ſaid to be in the likeneſs of him that was confeſſedly ſo.</p>
            <p>True it is, that we do not depart from the Stile of the Scripture, when we ſay, That Man, bounded and limited as he is, bears the Image of God; ſince God himſelf expreſſeth himſelf ſo at the Creation,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26:</note> 
               <hi>Let us make man in our Image, after our likeneſs:</hi> and in the New Creation this Image is new drawn in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and true Holineſs. It cannot be denied but that the Beams God communicates to man, do form a little Image of ſome of his Attributes: but beſides that, it was never ſaid of any man, that he was in the Form of God, before that he was man: St. <hi>Paul</hi> delivers himſelf in ſuch a manner, as makes it manifeſt, that the Divine Form he attributes to Jeſus Chriſt, was not an Image de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the Original, as is that which God communicates to men: We need only ſum all the Apoſtle's Words together, if we would fully comprehend his meaning: <hi>Who being in the form of God, thought it no robbery to be equal with God; but emptied himſelf, and took upon him the form of a ſervant, and was made in the likeneſs of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:55198:6"/>
            <p>Bleſſed be God, we live in a time, wherein there is no need at all to prove that our Saviour was really Man. Though this Truth be unqueſtionable, yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes no difficulty to aſſert, that Jeſus Chriſt took upon him the Form of a Servant, and that he was made in the likeneſs of men. At preſent we would not give the hearing to men, who by ſome trifling Niceties ſhould go about to renew an old Error, and prove that our Lord only clothed himſelf with ſome appearances of our Nature, becauſe forſooth, our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, That he took upon him the Form of a Servant, and was made in the Likeneſs of men; that is, had a Human Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance only. But we are all convinc'd, that this Form, and this Likeneſs, were upheld by the Reality of our Nature; that is to ſay, That our Saviour was truly man.</p>
            <p>This is an excellent Commentary on the words of St. <hi>Paul:</hi> we enquire what his meaning is, when he aſſures us, that Jeſus Chriſt was in the Form of God. He himſelf acquaints us what was his meaning, by ſaying of Jeſus Chriſt, who was true Man, That he took upon him the Form of a Servant, and the Likeneſs of Man. Make we uſe therefore of the Key he affords us, and we ſhall find, that to be in the Form of God, is to be really and truly God. The Oppoſition that is here evidently intended, would by no means be juſt, if in the one part Figure only was meant, and in the other Reality. Reality muſt be oppos'd to Reality: In the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Member of this Oppoſition, mention is made of the Reality of the Human Nature of Jeſus Chriſt; wherefore it is neceſſary, that in the former part the Reality of the Divine Nature of our Saviour ſhould be intended too. Being in the Form of God, he took upon him the Form of a Servant, and the Likeneſs of Man. St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth not ſay, Having taken upon him the Form of God, becauſe our Saviour was inveſted with it from Eternity. This Expreſſion doth not comport with an Eternal Divinity. But of the Human Nature he faith, That Jeſus Chriſt took it upon him, that being a thing which was done in Time; ſaving this only, the Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is exact: Our Bleſſed Saviour is as truly God, as he is Man.</p>
            <p>The Word Form; in this place, includes the Nature whoſe Form it is. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the Term St. <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth here; whence is derived the Name of the <hi>Anthroponorphites</hi> of old. They were ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they attributed a Human Form to God. The Form, ſay we, not meer Appearances only. They believed that God really had
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55198:7"/>a Body, Eyes, Ears, Hands and Paſſions; and in a word, that he was the Original of our Nature. So true it is that the Word Form doth not always imply meer Appearances: But that which muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the Sgnification of it, is, as we have already obſerved, the ſenſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> put upon it in the Sequel.</p>
            <p>If you demand why he makes uſe of this word, inſtead of ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſimply, Being God; for would not this have been much more explicite, than to ſay, Being in the Form of God? I might an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that it would be an unjuſt piece of Criticiſm to deſire a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe knowledge, why a Sacred Author makes uſe of one word ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than another. But without being reduc'd to this Anſwer, we have one more exact to the Queſtion. We can inform you why St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of Jeſus Chriſt, That he was in the Form of God, rather than that he was God.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ly.</hi> Becauſe indeed he was God by way of Image; he is the Image of the Inviſible God, ſaith St. <hi>Paul;</hi> he is the Brightneſs of his Glory, the Expreſs Image of the Perſon of God his Father. The Father, as you ſee, poſſeſſeth his Godhead by way of Principle, Source, and Original; whereas the Son hath his Divinity by way of Emanation, Derivation, and by way of Image. He is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and a living Image of the Living God. Were it permitted me to expreſs my ſelf in any other Language but that of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I would ſay with <hi>Tertullian, God of God, Light of Light;</hi> or with <hi>St. Gregory,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Neocaeſarea,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Thaumaturgas, The true Son of a True Father; Inviſible from the Inviſible; Incorruptible of the Incorruptible; Immortal of the Immortal; Eternal of the Eternal.</hi> Theſe Famous Doctors liv'd before the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council; ſo that we cannot accuſe theſe Expreſſions for being the Fruit of the Violence or Superſtition of the following Centuries. We have alledged theſe Fragments of pure Antiquity, only to ſhew by theſe, what kind of Image the Word of God is. Now foraſmuch as he is God in this manner, it was very proper and natural for St. <hi>Paul</hi> to ſay, <hi>Who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the form of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Reaſon why the Apoſtle expreſſeth himſelf thus, is, Becauſe by the Form of God, which he attributes to our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, he inſinuates ſomewhat more than the meer Divine Nature; for this Word denotes the Majeſty, and if I may ſo ſpeak, the Pomp and Glory of the Divine Nature.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:55198:7"/>
            <p>We ſhall be convinced of this Truth, if we will make uſe of the Light which the other Member of the oppoſition affords us. To be in the <hi>Form of a Servant,</hi> and in the <hi>Likeneſs of Man,</hi> implies not only to be poſſeſſed of the Human Nature, but to be clothed with thoſe Infirmities which conſtitute the External Form, as it were, thereof.</p>
            <p>So that we ſee that St. <hi>Paul</hi> when he ſaith that our Saviour was in the <hi>Form of God,</hi> he would thereby not only intimate to us that Chriſt was God, but that he had the Appearance and the Majeſty of a God; ſurrounded with Glory, worſhipped by the Angels, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of the Creatures; being in this ſtate he was willing to be made Man, and to expoſe himſelf to our Infirmities. The word <hi>Form</hi> made uſe of in both the Members of the oppoſitions, ſerves only to make it the more Expreſs and Emphatical.</p>
            <p>The third Propoſition is, That Jeſus Chriſt did not <hi>think is Robbery to be equal with God.</hi> This Propoſition hath two parts; the firſt is, <hi>He did not think it Robbery;</hi> that is, he did not judge it to be any Uſurpation; and as we conceive, that there is a <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure call'd Diminution,</hi> in theſe words, when God ſaith in the Third Commandment, <hi>that he will not hold him Guiltleſs,</hi> (inſtead of ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he will hold him guilty in a high degree,) <hi>that taketh his Name in vain.</hi> In like manner we ſay, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> when he ſaith that our Saviour did not think it Robbery, ſaith in effect, that he lookt upon it as a moſt juſt thing to <hi>make</hi> himſelf equal with God. The ſecond part of the Propoſition is, <hi>To make himſelf equal with God.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt ſtands <hi>upon equal ground</hi> with his Father; it is in the Original <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>things equal with God,</hi> which may be was not expreſt thus in the plural number without a particular deſign, even to teach us that Jeſus Chriſt is Eſſentially equal in all things with God: For tho, to ſpeak properly, there are no different things in God, and that his Eſſence is moſt perfectly one, and ſimple; yet our way of conceiving of it doth <hi>multiply it.</hi> We commonly imagine that the Attributes of God are very different things. St. <hi>Paul</hi> intending to teach us, that our Saviour was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly equal with God, ſaith, that <hi>he thought it no Robbery to be equal with God;</hi> that is, not only in Holineſs in Power, in Goodneſs, in Glory, but in whatſoever elſe is the Root and Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Divine Nature;<note place="margin">Col. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>In him dwelleth all the fulneſs of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head bodily.</hi> The <hi>plural number</hi> therefore ſeems very Emphatical in this place. Join we now both theſe Members of the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55198:8"/>together again: And then conſidering it thus whole and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, it imports thus much, That our Lord, who was fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his own Rights, made no difficulty to equalize him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with God; <hi>He thought it no Robbery to be equal with God;</hi> which is the moſt Natural and Literal Explication of the words of St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On what occaſion did our Saviour thus expreſs himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Glory of his Divine Nature? Some very Orthodox Interpreters make St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, That Jeſus Chriſt would not have thought it Robbery to be equal with God; which affords a meaning ſomewhat different from that of the ordinary Verſion, which ſaith, That Chriſt <hi>thought it no robbery to be equal with God.</hi> Both theſe meanings, the one as well as the other, ſuppoſe the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt. But we ſee no neceſſity to depart from our Verſion; and ſo much the leſs, becauſe it changeth nothing in the Original. The ſenſe it offers us, and which we have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, engageth us to ſhew on what occaſion our Lord Jeſus Chriſt attributes to himſelf an Equality with God.</p>
            <p>To reduce our ſelves to ſome compaſs, we will confine our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the one half of a Chapter of the Goſpel. In which lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle compaſs we ſhall meet with ſufficient Evidence of the Glory of Jeſus Chriſt. The fifth Chapter of the Goſpel of St. <hi>John</hi> is that which we have pitched upon for this purpoſe. Where at firſt it is manifeſt that the day of this Glory was a Solemn Feaſt amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> whom Devotion had brought together; our Saviour takes this occaſion to have the more Witneſſes of his Glory. In the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Verſes mention is made of an Angel, who troubling the Waters of the Pool of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> made it a Soveraign Bath for the Curing of the firſt Sick Perſon that was caſt into it. A poor Wretch that had been Thirty eight Years troubled with the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, had this ſuperadded to his Affliction, that he could not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Bleſſing of this Miracle, becauſe when the Water was troubled, he having no Body to put him in, another ſtill ſtept in before him. He whom the Angels worſhip, preſents himſelf to this poor Paralytick for his Comfort, and ſaith to him, <hi>Riſe, take up thy bed, and walk.</hi> And immediately the Man was made whole, and took up his Bed and walked. See here the voice of God, and not of Man. Our Saviour ſpeaks with Authority, as being the Lord and Maſter of Nature; <hi>Riſe, go out, hold thy Peace, be thou healed,</hi> &amp;c. He commanded the Winds, and the Sea, Devils,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55198:8"/>Diſeaſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Miniſters who receiv'd the Gift of Miracles from him, did not expreſs themſelves with the ſame Authority; it doth not belong to any one, but him who is equal with God, to ſpeak as God.</p>
            <p>The Evangeliſt obſerves, that our Saviour afterwards met with this Perſon he had healed, in the Temple, and ſaid to him, <hi>Behold thou art made whole, ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing befall thee.</hi> This Man had obtained the health of his Soul, the Remiſſion of his Sins, as well as the Health of his Body; our Saviour commonly grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them both together. This gives us occaſion to take notice with what Authority he forgave Sins. On a certain time having ſeen another Man ſick of the Palſie, he ſaid unto him, <hi>Man, thy ſins are forgiven thee.</hi> Whereupon immediately the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees begin to reaſon with themſelves, ſaying, <hi>Who is this that ſpeaks Blaſphemy? Who is it that can forgive Sins, but God alone?</hi> The Principle they went upon was good and ſound; none but God alone, to ſpeak properly, can forgive Sin; for when Men abſolve, they do no more but ſimply declare that ſuch Sins are pardon'd; he muſt be equal to God that pardons Sins Authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively and Principally. Our Lord according to his Omniſcience having diſcover'd theſe Thoughts of the Scribes and Phariſees, ſaith unto them, <hi>Why do you reaſon in your hearts? for which is eaſier to ſay, Thy ſins are forgiven thee, or, riſe up and walk? but that ye may know that the Son of Man hath authority upon earth to forgive ſin; I ſay unto thee, Riſe, take up thy bed and walk.</hi> The Queſtion was not, Whether our Saviour had the power of declaring, as the Miniſters of the Goſpel do, that ſuch and ſuch Sins are pardoned. No, he is accus'd here of having Blaſphemed, and of having uſurpt the Rights of God himſelf, that is to ſay, that he had pronounced Abſolution Magiſterially and Independently. Do we find Jeſus Chriſt putting by this as a Calumny? Not in the leaſt; he leaves the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Opinion wherein they were, of his having ſpoke like God; and adds, that he had right ſo to do: <hi>But that you may know that the Son of Man hath power upon earth to forgive ſin,</hi> he ſaith to the Man ſick of the Palſie, what? not, thy Sins are pardoned; <hi>but riſe, take up thy bed, and go to thy houſe;</hi> to the end theſe Zealots may know by this Miracle who I am. It was thus that the Sins of the Man ſick of the Palſie had been forgiven in the fifth Chapter of St. <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:55198:9"/>
            <p>This Man goes and publiſheth the Cure that was wrought upon him, amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were offended at it, becauſe it had been done on the Sabbath Day. What doth our Lord to take off this Scandal? He anſwers, by making himſelf equal with God, <hi>My Father worketh hitherto, and I work alſo;</hi> that is as much as to ſay, There is no more Sabbath to me, than to my Father; the Law of Times and Feaſts doth not reach us. The <hi>Jews</hi> enrag'd to hear this anſwer from our Saviour, ſought to kill him, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſaith the Evangeliſt, becauſe he had broken the Sabbath, but ſaid alſo, that God was his Father, making himſelf equal with God. If it had not been ſo, our Lord would not have fail'd to deteſt the Blaſphemy: But inſtead of this, he proves that he had reaſon to make himſelf equal with God, and carries this equality to the very higheſt pitch of Glory: <hi>For as the Father raiſeth up the dead, and quickneth them,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>even ſo the Son quickneth whom he will; that all men ſhould honour the Son, even as they honour the Father; verily, verily I ſay unto you, the hour is coming, and now is, when the dead ſhall hear the voice of the Son of God, and they that hear ſhall live. For as the Father hath life in himſelf, ſo hath he given to the Son to have life in himſelf.</hi> 'Tis impoſſible for any one to equal himſelf more poſitively with God, than our Saviour here doth in theſe words: They do not in the leaſt ſtand in need of a Commentary to allow us to ſay with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> That our Bleſſed Saviour thought it no Robbery to be equal with God his Father.</p>
            <p>This Literal Senſe we have hitherto explained, may be further illuſtrated by ſeveral Oppoſitions. Can we make any queſtion, but that St. <hi>Paul</hi> in propoſing this great Truth to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> had an Eye to the falſe Apotheoſis of Paganiſm. Amongſt thoſe gods that the World worſhipp'd, there were ſome that never had been, others that were no more; and a third ſort that were yet in being, but were nothing leſs than gods. The gods that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had been owed their Original to Poeſie and Fable: The gods that had been M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, but were dead, had been honour'd this way, either out of Thankfulneſs, or out of Policy; the gods that were yet in being, but that were nothing leſs than gods, were Men yet alive, to whom baſe Flattery erected Altars. All was full of Robbery, nothing was ſeen but Sacriledge, and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations of the Divinity. St. <hi>Paul</hi> in oppoſition to all theſe Falſe gods, ſaith, that our Lord and Saviour was in the Form of God, before ever he was known by Men; they were not Men therefore
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55198:9"/>that put him in the Form of God. Their Divinities were made ſuch by the Adoration that was paid them by Men; which made <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſay, That to ſpeak properly, it was indeed Man that was propitious to God, becauſe he could not become God, till after it had pleas'd Man to declare him ſuch. But the difference is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious on our Saviour's ſide, he was God before that ever Men knew him, or worſhipp'd him; yea, even before Men were. Poetical Fiction, Reaſon of State, Gratitude, Flattery, or Superſtition, had no part here. <hi>From everlaſting to everlaſting thou art God.</hi> The Men that were worſhipp'd, whilſt yet alive, eaſily perceiv'd that they were no gods; they were very ſenſible that the Divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours rendred unto them, were no better than Robbery. But, ſaith St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt thought it no Robbery to be equal with God; in which words there is a tacite oppoſition to that Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination which Paganiſm had eſtabliſh'd amongſt their gods. They ſaid, that <hi>Jupiter</hi> was the Maſter and Lord Paramount of their gods, there being none on equal ground with him. St. <hi>Paul</hi> here inſinuates, that Jeſus Chriſt is really greater than all the Pagan gods were, even in the Conceit of thoſe that were their Worſhippers. He is equal to God, to that Great God who is the Soveraign Maſter and Lord of the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe oppoſitions which the Apoſtle had an eye to in the words we are explaining, it ſeems probable, that he had a more particular regard to a matter wherein the <hi>Philippians</hi> were more particularly concern'd. They conceiv'd it no ſmall part of their Glory, that their Countrey had produc'd <hi>Alexander the Great.</hi> This Conqueror conceiv'd it was both his Glory and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, to be worſhipp'd as a god. He would needs be thought the Son of <hi>Jupiter;</hi> and not being content to have pillaged the Earth, was deſirous to carry his Uſurpations to Heaven. He knew well enough that the Quality he Arrogated to himſelf of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> was a true piece of Robbery. The power of Truth oblig'd this Falſe god to ſay, during the pains he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd by the Wound he had received from an Arrow. That they would make him the Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> but that he ſelf well enough that he was but a Man. The <hi>Philippians</hi> were fully acquainted with this Story; St. <hi>Paul</hi> knew it, and we may aver, that he thought of it in preſenting to the <hi>Philippians</hi> a Saviour who was really and truly God, the true Son of the true God; <hi>who being in the Form of God, thought it no robbery to be equal with God.</hi> All
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55198:10"/>theſe oppoſitions are of great uſe to illuſtrate the Literal Senſe we have explained.</p>
            <p>It is time now to ſearch into the Doctrine it contains, which we ſhall do by conſidering it firſt in a Relative, and then in an Abſolute Senſe. In a Relative Senſe it will be to purpoſe to know the Characters, firſt of him who is here ſpoken of; ſecondly of him who ſpeaks; and thirdly of thoſe to whom it is ſpoken.</p>
            <p>He concerning whom here is ſpoken, was on the one hand the Pattern of an Abſolute Humility, and on the other a great Zealot for the Glory of God. If we have caſt our Eyes never ſo little upon the Goſpel, we ſhall find this to be a Truth altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conteſtable. Our Lord Jeſus himſelf hath given us a great and ſignal inſtance of the Humility which he recommends; he waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Diſciples Feet, he ſuffers Injuries patiently, he flees Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. On the other hand, How nice and tender do we find him, in caſes where his Father's Glory was concern'd? Doth he perceive that the Laws of God are made to truckle to the Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men? With what force do we ſee him exaggerate this Affront? If he ſees Men prophane the Houſe of God, by changing it to a Market-place, he does not think words ſufficient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs this Inſolence, he makes a Whip of Cords to laſh theſe Prophane Wretches out of the Temple. With this double Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, which might be made out by many more paſſages of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; at what a rate think you would our Saviour have delivered himſelf, if ever he had met with one that made himſelf a god? This was a time wherein the <hi>Jews</hi> were not guilty of groſs Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and wherein <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had baniſh'd the Idols of other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: ſo that our Lord had no occaſion to declare againſt Idols; but had he met with any, what would not he have ſaid? Had he taken notice of any Man that arrogated to himſelf Divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, with what Zeal and Vehemence would he have confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Pride of that Uſurper? We know enough of the Spirit of our Lord on other occaſions, to juſtifie what we ſuppoſe of him? What then ought we to conclude from this, that he who was ſo Humble and ſo Zealous, yet made himſelf equal with God? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be ſaid here that is conſiſtent with Reaſon, but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that he was really that, for which he would that Men ſhould take him. Had not he been God, and conſequently equal to God his Father, he would have been ſo far from affecting this Equality, that he would have abhorr'd the leaſt tendency that way. Inſtead
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55198:10"/>of ſpeaking Magiſterially, he would always have expreſt himſelf in the moſt humble ſtile imaginable, to diſabuſe the People, who by the Fame of his Miracles would have been tempted to take him for a God. But we find his Conduct quite oppoſite to this; he doth not think it any <hi>Robbery to be equal with God:</hi> But how can this be, if he be not God indeed? What is become of his Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity? What of his Zeal? What of his Sincerity? Theſe three Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are the Sureties and Pledges for our Faith of the Godhead of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Who is it that writes this? 'Tis St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that is to ſay in one word, whatſoever can be conceiv'd of Zeal againſt attributing the Divine Glory to a Creature. This Apoſtle met with ſeveral occaſions to make himſelf known under this Character. He ſtrongly declares himſelf againſt Idolatry in ſeveral places. In the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles</hi> we find what a Reception he gave to thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Honours, which the <hi>Lycaonians</hi> would needs force upon him; he rents his Clothes, runs in amongſt them, <hi>Crying out, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>Sirs, why do you theſe things? We are alſo men of like paſſions with you, and preach unto you, that ye ſhould turn from theſe vanities unto the living God.</hi> In the Seventeenth Chapter of the ſame Book we find that the Spirit of St. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſtirred in him at the ſight of the Idols they worſhipp'd at <hi>Athens.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17.16.</note> In the firſt Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> we find him thundring againſt Idolaters, ſaying, that they <hi>changed the glory of the incorruptible God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 1.23, 25.</note> 
               <hi>into an image made like to corruptible man, and worſhipped and ſerved the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more than the Creator, who is bleſſed for ever.</hi> This is enough to give us a taſte of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Spirit in this matter, and to ſhew that he had the greateſt horror for Idolatry. Beſides this, he made it always his buſineſs to humble and abaſe the Creature, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the greater Glory might redound to the Creator, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all thoſe things that might in the leaſt ſerve to colour the Religious Worſhip of the Creature. Yet for all this, he ſpeaks always moſt magnificently of Jeſus Chriſt; he makes him equal with the Soveraign God, who hath created Heaven and Earth. What therefore can St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Thoughts be in ſpeaking thus? Muſt we not look upon him to be the moſt imprudent of all Men, in making our Saviour ſo great, in caſe he be not God? At this rate we muſt not leave to our Apoſtle not ſo much as common Senſe. We are agreed that he abhors the Religious Worſhip of the Creature, and at the ſame time own that he ſets the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55198:11"/>upon the Altar. This therefore engageth us to declare, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a Mad-man, or that Jeſus Chriſt was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed God bleſſed for ever. Neither will the Enemies of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity be ever able to juſtifie the Apoſtle's Wiſdom, by ſaying, that the Man whom he makes ſo great, was not an ordinary Man: Let him be an Angel, let him be more than the Angels, if he be a Creature, he is infinitely below God. Let us conceive a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as glorious as it is poſſible for any Creature to be, there will ſtill be an infinite difference between it and the Creator. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without the greateſt imprudence ſay of it, that it is equal to the Creator; it would be utterly abſurd to make a God of this Creature, however advanced or dignify'd. This is the Honour put upon St. <hi>Paul,</hi> by thoſe who affirm, that this Jeſus, whoſe Glory he exalts ſo extreamly, was no more than a meer Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>And whom doth this St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak to? To the <hi>Philippians,</hi> that is, to Chriſtians that had been either Jews or Heathens; how untowardly did our Apoſtle go about to confirm them in their Vocation, if Jeſus Chriſt had not been God? He hath to do with People who were apt enough to take offence at this Truth. Theſe Chriſtians that before had been Jews, were perſwaded from their Infancy, that it was a Crime of the higheſt Nature for any man to make himſelf equal with God. They had been Inſtructed, that for a like piece of Inſolence the chief of the Angels had loſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, together with his whole Faction. This was the very Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that of all others was neareſt to God, and yet becauſe he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd to a greater nearneſs, he was caſt headlong into the Bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit. They knew that the Firſt Man fell into disfavour with his Creator, for having affected to be as God. They had been converſant in the Writing of the Prophets, where they had been informed that God deteſts nothing more than Pride, which made Man forget the meanneſs and lowneſs of his Nature. Amongſt other paſſages, they had not forgot the Deſcription the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> makes of the King of <hi>Babylon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 14.12.</note> 
               <hi>How art thou fallen from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, O Lucifer, ſon of the morning! &amp;c. For thou haſt ſaid in thine heart, I will aſcend into heaven, I will exalt my throne above the ſtars of God, &amp;c. I will aſcend above the heights of the clouds, I will be like the moſt high; yet ſhalt thou be brought down to hell.</hi> The Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Prophets againſt Idolatry had made ſuch an Impreſſion on the Spirit of the <hi>Jews</hi> at the time that St. <hi>Paul</hi> writ this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55198:11"/>Epiſtle, that there was no Sin which they did more abhor and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt than this. We know what happen'd when <hi>Pilate</hi> undertook to put ſome Shields into the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> they were ſain to take them away from thence, becauſe the People were offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee the Faces of the <hi>Roman Caeſars</hi> upon them. <hi>Herod</hi> alſo having Erected Trophies in that Holy Place, could not appeaſe the Tumult, but by ſhewing them, that no Human Figure was found in them. It is notorious alſo what happened when <hi>Herod</hi> had the Boldneſs to place an Eagle over the Gate of the Temple. Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is full of the Effects of the Tenderneſs of the <hi>Jews</hi> with reſpect to Idolatry at the Time of the Birth of Chriſtianiſm. We muſt here diſtinguiſh the Times; for it is certain, that in the time of the Prophets the Jews, as by a Spirit of Contradiction, run mad after Idols: Neither did they begin to be wiſe in this Point, till after the ceaſing of the Prophets.</p>
            <p>It is no leſs inconteſtable, that the moſt of the Chriſtians of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippi</hi> had in their Education been made very ſenſible of any thing that approacht to the Worſhip of the Creature. What therefore could be St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s meaning in propoſing to them a Jeſus, who makes himſelf equal with God, if indeed Jeſus had not been God? This was a Capital Error, and would have been the ready way to make the Chriſtians to return to the Synagogue whence they were come forth. If we will but allow our Apoſtle to have had any tolerable remainder of Senſe and Underſtanding, we muſt own that the Fear of incenſing them to the utmoſt, would have made him ſuppreſs what he ſaith of our Saviour, if ſo be he had not been God; if he had not really been that which the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> pretended to be. We add this word, becauſe it is very probable that St. <hi>Paul</hi> in our Text, made an Alluſion to this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, wherein <hi>Iſaiah</hi> repreſents a King, whom he calls by way of deriſion, <hi>Star of the Morning;</hi> and who after having made himſelf like to the moſt High, is ſorely againſt his Will hurl'd down to the Grave. It was a piece of manifeſt Robbery for this proud Monarch to take ſo ſoaring a flight. I will ſhew you, ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who is the true Morning-Star, truly equal with God, and the very true God, and who notwithſtanding all theſe Tranſcendent Advantages, humbled and emptied himſelf, and that voluntarily: It is no other than Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>who being in the form of God, thought it no robbery to be equal with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:55198:12"/>
            <p>Return we now to the ſecond Order of Chriſtians to whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> writes; theſe were the Converted Heathens, who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the multitude of their Gods. They had been made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd of a Plurality, injurious to the Supream Lord of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; and they had ſuffer'd themſelves to be perſuaded, that this God all alone was poſſeſt of the whole Glory of the Deity. Themſelves are become the Adverſaries of the Religion they had forſaken; they are aſtoniſht to think how formerly they could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a plurality of gods; they deride the Error that communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates the Divinity to many Beings, and thoſe fooliſh Genealogies that furniſh <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> with Children. Let ſomebody tell us now, what is become of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Wiſdom, to ſpeak to a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Temper, of a Son of God, of a Jeſus equal with God? Would not they have ſtop'd his Mouth with ſome ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn as this? You plunge us into the ſame Errors, whence you your ſelf have ſo lately retrieved us. You have made us Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by perſwading us that there is but One God; we have believed it; and now you come and violate this inculcated Unity. I appeal to any Rational man, whether any thing leſs than the invincible ſtrength of Truth, could have allowed St. <hi>Paul</hi> to deliver any thing like the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt? He formerly aſſerts it, though indeed if he had only ſpoken of it in ſuch a manner as to leave the matter in doubt, we muſt own, that even this would have been a great Imprudence in St. <hi>Paul</hi> to advance ſo far as this; foraſmuch as by this means he would have ruined the work of his Miniſtry. This is a convincing Argument to any one, never ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle acquainted with the great Prudence of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> how well he was perſwaded of the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Conſider we in the ſecond place, Chriſt's humbling and empty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of himſelf: <hi>But made himſelf of no reputation,</hi> as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation renders, what in the Original is, <hi>He emptied himſelf.</hi> I make no queſtion but it hath appeared ſtrange to ſome, that I have ſo long inſiſted on the Glory of our Saviour on a Day ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized in memory of his Humiliation. But they will be ſatisfied, by conſidering the Myſtery they have heard explained; It is the Myſtery by way of Eminence; it is the Myſtery that ſets off all all other Myſteries; 'tis the Myſtery without which the Chriſtian Religion would contain no Myſtery at all: For if we conſider it independently from the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt, we ſhall find our Religion to contain nothing that is Great or Sublime. The
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55198:12"/>whole of it will only amount to this, That a Teacher comes to inſtruct men by exact Morality, and by a perfect example, with regard to thoſe Virtues we ought to practiſe in our lives; but againſt whom there are ſome things to be objected with reſpect to thoſe Virtues that are of uſe at the point of death. What a mean Idea would they fain give us of Chriſt and his Religion? St. <hi>Paul</hi> in this caſe would have been quite beſides the matter in ſaying, <hi>Without controverſy great is the myſtery of godlineſs.</hi> We know that our Apoſtle uttered himſelf thus by way of oppoſition to other Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; particularly to the Myſteries of Paganiſm, and by a more ſpecial manner in oppoſition to the Myſteries of the <hi>Great Diana,</hi> Goddeſs of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> where <hi>Timothy</hi> made his abode: In this City the ordinary Cry was, <hi>Great, Great is Diana of the Epheſians:</hi> In oppoſition to which, the Cry of St. <hi>Paul</hi> is, <hi>Great, great is the myſtery of godlineſs:</hi> yea, <hi>without controverſy, great is the myſtery of godlineſs.</hi> What reaſon was there for all this a do? For all theſe poſitive Aſſertions, if Jeſus Chriſt be no more than a meer man? But I very well apprehend St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when I conſider, that Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity preſents us a God manifeſted in Fleſh; for without all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, this is a great Myſtery, the greateſt that ever was heard of by men. This is that which ennobles the Chriſtian Religion, and 'tis from this Spring ſhe derives all her Glory. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in our Holy Religion which does not become precious and admirable, by the general influence of this great Myſtery. Can any one therefore juſtly accuſe us for having too long inſiſted on the Glory of our Lord, ſeeing it is alſo the entire Glory of our Religion?</p>
            <p>But that which altogether juſtifies our Method herein, is, That this day is properly Conſecrated to the Thankfulneſs we owe to God, for his infinite Love in ſending his Son into the World, and in delivering him up to Death, after having clothed him with our Nature. To this purpoſe it is of abſolute neceſſity for us to know the price and value of this Preſent. The greater it is, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er muſt be our Thankfulneſs. If Jeſus Chriſt be no more than a man, I dare boldly ſay, that his ſending of him, is not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt favour God hath beſtowed upon us. This ſuppoſed, we ſee little reaſon why the Goſpel ſhould inſiſt ſo ſtrongly and emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally upon this Divine Charity: Why doth it tell us <hi>of the riches of grace, of the exceeding excellent riches of grace in Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> Why doth it tell us, that <hi>God ſo loved the world, as to ſend his only begotten
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55198:13"/>Son? That God recommends his love unto us, in that when we were yet ſinners Chriſt died for us.</hi> Surely if Jeſus Chriſt be no more than a mere Man; yea, if he were no more than an Angel, the Point would never bear theſe Expreſſions; put but the name of Man where Chriſt is ſpoken of, and you'll be fain to own, that theſe paſſages have no ſenſe at all: God hath ſo loved men, that he ſent a man to hinder them from periſhing. What, is it ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd inſtance of Charity for God to ſend one Man, to ſave ſo many Millions of Men? This would have been no more than if he had given a ſtraw for to ſave them; ſurely there is no ſuch tranſcendent Love in all this. God hath to that degree recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his Love to us, that he hath ſent a Man to Dye for us. Where is the wonder in all this; where ſhall we look for this high recommendation of the Divine Love? If inſtead of a Man, it were an Angel, or ſome other Creature far more Glorious; yet would it not have bulk enough to fill up all theſe Paſſages. 'Tis no ſuch great matter to form a Creature on purpoſe to ſhew ſo many Millions of men the way to Life. And yet the Scripture prompts us to conceive of the Love of God, as of a thing that merits the Admiration of Men and Angels. Except therefore we take it for granted, that our Redeemer is God, we are at a loſs how to make any ſenſe at all of theſe Texts of Scripture. But no ſooner have we admitted this Myſtery, but we find that nothing indeed can be conceiv'd ſo great, as is this Love of God: We find that the ſending of Jeſus Chriſt, is <hi>the grace</hi> by way of <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence;</hi> we perceive that the Scripture hath not ſaid too much of it; and we confeſs, in a word, that it is impoſſible for us to make any anſwerable return for this infinite Mercy of God, by any other way than by an infinite Acknowledgment, were we capable of it.</p>
            <p>We have therefore ſpoke things ſuitable to the Day, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming you in your perſwaſion of the Divinity of our Saviour; for by this means we have powerfully excited your grateful Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment. Yea, we may ſay, that we have handled the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Point, in treating of the Firſt; ſo that there remains no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in a manner for us to ſay upon theſe Words of St. <hi>Paul, yet he humbled,</hi> or <hi>emptied himſelf.</hi> We had propoſed to our ſelves to make you ſenſible of the Greatneſs of our Saviour's Love, in Emptying himſelf for us: To compaſs this our intent, we have been oblig'd to meaſure both ends of this Myſtery; we have
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55198:13"/>drawn our Line from that end which was fartheſt from us, the leaſt ſenſible, and moſt unknown; I mean, we have begun with the Eternal Glory of Jeſus Chriſt; from which we muſt now paſs to the other end, or extremity; and conſider what Jeſus Chriſt is become; <hi>he became man;</hi> he humbled himſelf to the Death. There is no need of inſiſting long upon this ſecond Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, it is a thing known to us, we know what it is to be a Man; there is no need of any great Reaſoning, nor ſtrength of Faith to contemplate this part of our Myſtery. We need only to conſider our ſelves a little, and to ſum up all the infirmities of our Nature, Hunger, Thirſt, Wearineſs, Pain, Sorrow; for all theſe our Saviour took upon him: Yet is not this all, he was willing to taſte Death alſo; which is, as it were, the Center to which all our infirmities tend; and for an encreaſe of the Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Cup, he was willing to die a violent Death, a Death accompanied with the moſt exquiſite Pains, and the utmoſt Shame: Yet <hi>he humbled himſelf, he emptied himſelf, and took upon him the form of a ſervant, and was made in the likeneſs of men; and being found in faſhion as a man, he humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the croſs.</hi> In a Word, we ſee what this Humiliation of our Saviour is; he is become what we are; and as if the common infirmities of our Nature had not been ſufficient for him, he borrowed thoſe which human Juſtice inflicts upon the very worſt of Criminals; <hi>Nevertheleſs he emptied himſelf.</hi> O the vaſt diſtance there is betwixt the one of theſe ends and the other! O the immenſe interval there is betwixt the Abaſement of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Glory of his Eternal Deity! St. <hi>Paul</hi> paſſeth from one Abyſs to the other; from the Abyſs of Glory, to an Abyſs of Miſery: <hi>Who,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>being in the form of God, thought it no robbery to be equal with God; nevertheleſs he emptied himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a Beauty there appears in this oppoſition! This, in my mind, is one of thoſe Eloquent ſtrains in Scripture, that we ought to dwell upon with admiration. I ſpeak of an Eloquence truly great and ſublime, which naturally riſeth from the greatneſs of the things themſelves, and not from a pleaſing cadence of pick'd words. Nothing can be imagin'd to have more of this character in it, than theſe words, <hi>Nevertheleſs he emptied himſelf.</hi> What is admirable in this expreſſion, would be loſt and ſpoil'd, ſhould we go about to extend it by a more ample Explication. St. <hi>Paul</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the ſublime Character much better than our modern
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55198:14"/>Preachers; when they have got hold of a Myſtery, they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to raiſe it, and ſet it forth by the abundance of their words, and bring in Rhetorick to the aſſiſtance of their Divinity. Their Maſter did not do ſo, I mean St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ought to be the Maſter of all Preachers. He utters the greateſt things conceivable, almoſt without ſpeaking, and in one word lays open the deepeſt Myſtery. To count words, we ſpeak much more than this our Apoſtle; but to weigh things, we ſpeak much leſs. We deceive our ſelves if we think we are able by the help of words, to give a greater Idea of the Myſtery we purpoſe to explain; in doing ſo, we only take pains to fill the Ear, without reaching the heart, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires but few words, as reſerving to her ſelf the right of enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon her ſubject, by Meditations and Reflections. Let us give credit herein to the Searcher of hearts, who often utter things by halves; and the Holy men Inſpired by him, do ſometimes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch upon their ſubjects, and leave the reſt for the Heart to ſupply. St. <hi>Paul</hi> in ſaying nothing of what he had ſeen and heard in the Third Heaven, ſaith more than if he had made a long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Glory of the Bleſſed. Theſe are things, ſaith he, which it is not lawful for a man to utter. See here, Believer, matter indeed to employ thy Meditation, until thou thy ſelf arrive to that Place of never-failing Bliſs. Our Holy Apoſtle obſerves much the ſame meaſures, when he delivers himſelf on the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Revelation, and leaves a Myſtery, if I may ſay ſo, in thoſe Myſteries. Not as if he would withhold ought of the Counſel of God from us, for what he doth not ſay in one place, he doth in another. This is a kind of reſervedneſs which honours the Myſtery, and gives a greater Idea of it. What Exclamations, what Figures would not an Orator of the World have made uſe of, upon that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> delivers in the 11th. Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> concerning the Rejection of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Calling of the <hi>Gentiles?</hi> Whereas the Man of God wraps all up in theſe few words; <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God! how unſearchable are his judgments, and his ways paſt finding out!</hi> He leaves the Believer, in a deep contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, on the brink of this Abyſs. This is Eloquence indeed!</p>
            <p>We may perceive a Ray of this Divine Eloquence, in the Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> now before us; <hi>Nevertheleſs he emptied himſelf.</hi> We will not go about to explain theſe Words, for fear of leſſening their force; let them enter without attendance into your Hearts; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55198:14"/>them in their genuine and natural Import. I require nothing elſe of you, ſave only that you would often ſay to your ſelves, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, he emptied himſelf:</hi> Chriſt is God, <hi>Nevertheleſs, he empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf:</hi> This alone is enough to excite your admiration. We have reaſon to queſtion, whether a Soul, were it left to its choice, would be willing to become incarnate in a Body, ſubject to all our Infirmities. Some Wiſe Men have frankly declar'd themſelves, That they would not become young again if it were in their power. Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the moſt part of men would not be of this Opinion, eſpecially thoſe who have led a pleaſant Life: but if one ſhould propoſe to them a Life of Thirty Four Years, full of Miſeries, and to end at laſt by the Death of the Croſs, think you they would accept of a Life on theſe Terms? A Soul would never conſent to ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation; and an Angel much leſs. Return we to our Text; Chriſt is God, it was not an Human Soul; it was not an Angel; He is God; he was God; <hi>Nevertheleſs, he emptied himſelf.</hi> Creatures would be very unwilling to enter into Partnerſhip with a Nature loaden with Infirmities; and yet Jeſus Chriſt, the Creator, was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to empty himſelf. An Abyſs as impenetrable to Angels, as it is to us! Ye Angels, ye are aſtoniſhed to ſee that he hath done that, which ye would not have been willing to do! you cannot found the bottom of this Myſtery; you are as well as we, on the brink of this Abyſs; you ſay as we do; Oh Riches! Oh Depth! Chriſt is God; <hi>Nevertheleſs he emptied himſelf!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He who was in the Beginning, was willing to be made of a Woman, in the fulneſs of time. He who was rich, became poor; He who is Immortal, hath ſhed his own Blood. We make uſe of the expreſs Terms of Scripture, that we may not give the mind of Man the Liberty of making Oppoſitions now, that might prove injurious to the Majeſty of our Saviour. He was made Man, but he always continued to be God. The Deity is unchangeable, and was always Glorious, even after that it had emptied it ſelf; but u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niting perſonally with the Man Jeſus, it appropriated to it ſelf all the Infirmities of this Second Nature; and it is true to ſay, That God emptied himſelf, that he was made man, that he ſhed his Blood. It would be matter of trouble to us, ſhould you believe, that the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt paſſed through all theſe Degrees of Abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; No, this is impoſſible; it is of the Eſſence of God always to continue God. Jeſus Chriſt is in this reſpect, the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever. He has therefore only emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55198:15"/>himſelf, by entring into Union with an Infirm and Mortal Man, in ſuch a manner, as that the two Natures conſtitute only one Perſon, much after the ſame manner as the Soul and Body, united by the Bonds of Life, make only one Perſon. This Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which we have thought neceſſary, doth not hinder, but that there remain ſtill many Wonders in the Myſtery of the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. It is always true, that the Word hath emptied it ſelf; It is always true, that our great God and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, hath found the Secret to be made Man, and to humble himſelf for us.</p>
            <p>We have in this Myſtery two great Motives to Gratitude, the Birth and Death of Jeſus Chriſt. The Child is born to us, the Son is given to us; we celebrate in one and the ſame Day, two great Feſtivals, <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> and <hi>Eaſter.</hi> It is our duty to ſolemnize them by a redoubling of our Zeal; one only of theſe Myſteries claims all our Thankfulneſs. What ſhall we do for a God who was willing for our ſakes, to live after the manner of men? The Eternal Word, which had no need of us, hath emptied himſelf for to make us happy. O Adorable Word! Thou hadſt not the ſame concern for the Angels that have left their Station: Thou haſt not clothed thy ſelf with their Nature, though more excellent than ours, but haſt honoured our Earth in taking it upon thee. Our merciful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer was willing to paſs through the Womb of a Virgin, there to take upon him Fleſh like ours. What ſhall we render to God for ſo great a Favour! Let us take the Cup of Bleſſing, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God in the Language of Angels, <hi>Glory be to God on high.</hi> Let us glorifie him as much as is poſſible for us. Could we ſpeak to the Angels, as they ſpake to the Shepherds, we would repeat to thoſe Bleſſed Spirits, the Words which they themſelves have taught us; <hi>This day a Child is born to us; Glory be to God in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</hi> We cannot ſufficiently glorifie him here on Earth, do ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore help us to glorifie him. If we be not able to render unto our Saviour all the Glory that is due unto him for his Birth, what ſhall we ſay with reſpect to his Death, which we have this Morning celebrated? It was much in him to be born for us; but it is much more to die for us. What! have our hearts nothing to ſay on occaſion of this Death? Sure had they been dumb, or inſenſible as to the Myſtery of the Incarnation, ſhall not the Death of Chriſt put life into them? What can have any power over you, if this Death can make no Impreſſion upon you? Pray what will be able to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55198:15"/>move you? What will be able to engage you to ſerve God, if this do not? But I don't conſider that I am ſpeaking to thoſe, who for the moſt part have been entertain'd at the Lord's Table: If all that Funeral Furniture, wherewith he appears in the Euchariſt; if theſe Sacred Symbols, which convey, as it were, the Death of Jeſus Chriſt into your very Bowels, have not been able to move your Hearts, no Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon will be of force enough to ſtir them. In this caſe your heart muſt be altogether inſenſible, ſo that Words can have no effect upon it.</p>
            <p>We may ſuppoſe therefore, that before your entring into this place, you have fill'd your Souls with that double Solemnity, to which this Day invites you; and that after having ſeriouſly medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated the Birth and Death of our Saviour, you have put your ſelves into a State of Repentance, you have put on your Wedding Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to go to meet your Bridegroom. We muſt alſo ſuppoſe that you have renewed your Repentance, in approaching to this Holy Table. It is a hard thing, ſo nearly to behold what our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord hath done for us, without being pierc'd and penetrated thereby. At this happy meeting of your Heart, with the Mercy of God, you have bewailed your Sins, and have promiſed a more holy Converſation for time to come. We cannot believe that ſince that happy Moment you have chang'd your thoughts, you are ſtill the ſame, and your Piety ſtill preſerves all its heat; for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what would be comparable to your Inconſtancy? what! in two hours time to change your moſt ſolemn Vows and Promiſes into Perjuries! this is ſcarce poſſible. We ſuppoſe therefore, that you are ſtill in that good ſtate, even in that ſtate of Repentance, wherein you were when you communicated.</p>
            <p>The only thing that ſtill remains for us to do, is to exhort you to perſevere in theſe holy Motions. We do not expect that you will always feel the ſame Unction, or that you will be always in the ſame Recollection; ſuch a ſtate is not conſiſtent with our Frame, nor with thoſe different kinds of life to which Providence hath tied us. But nothing can hinder you from performing your Promiſes; you may live, and live like Chriſtians. Were you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in ways of living, that were inconſiſtent with the Spirit of our Holy Religion, I would conjure you preſently to quit thoſe Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, wherein you could not be ſaved. We muſt live, 'tis true, but 'tis more neceſſary we ſhould be ſaved. <hi>What doth it profit a man to gain the whole world, if</hi> at the ſame time <hi>he loſeth his own ſoul?</hi> I can't think that amongſt thoſe that hear me, there is any perſon,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55198:16"/>whoſe Profeſſion is directly contrary to Salvation; but yet it is but too too viſible, that moſt Profeſſions have their Rocks, and their Dangers: Snares rain down upon all the Children of Men, as the Holy Spirit ſpeaks. All of you, as many as are here, apprehend well enough what I would ſay, to morrow or the next day, for I dare not ſay this day, will meet with theſe dangers, the occaſions in which you have been formerly worſted, will preſent themſelves again: Then be ſure to call to mind your Promiſes to God this Day: Repreſent this Holy Table to your Spirit; recall the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of this Day; be faithful to the Lord, and pay your Vows to the moſt High.</p>
            <p>We will not here run over the ſeveral Vertues, to which his Service engageth you; but we can do no leſs than ſpecifie thoſe to which St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts the <hi>Philippians,</hi> upon occaſion of our Lord's Example; who, when he was God, did notwithſtanding, ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe himſelf as to be made Man; yea, to that degree, as to die the Death of the Croſs. The two Vertues that are moſt dazling in this Example, are Humility and Charity. O how happy would this Day prove, might it ſee theſe two Virtues reigning in your Souls! We are naturally proud, and I don't know from whence that hardneſs and inſenſibility comes, that we have for our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; for even Nature inſpires us with more Charity, than ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in our Lives. Proud Souls, come and humble your ſelves in the preſence of the Child Jeſus; he who is God, was made Man, that ye, who are but mortal men, might be perſuaded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like God. Reſemble him in his Humility, not in his Glory; He hath condeſcended to put himſelf in a Condition, wherein he might be imitated. It was the Crime of our Firſt Parents, That they would be as God. Be ſatisfied, ye Poſterity of <hi>Adam,</hi> at preſent, it is a Vertue to be willing to reſemble God. Humble your ſelves as he humbled himſelf; who being God, was made Man: He hath, as you ſee, run through infinite ſpaces, to put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf within reach of us: From Glory he hath ſtept down into No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. You need not travel far to arrive at Annihilation, you have no more than a ſtep to take; your Nature hath plac'd you almoſt on the ſame Level with Nothing: You need only well to view and contemplate your ſelves, and preciſely keep your ſelves to the Idea of what you are, and you'll acknowledge, that you want little of being Nothing. Retire into your own Boſom, ſet aſide the Uſurpations of Self-love, and then tell us what you find over
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55198:16"/>and above. It may be your heart will bear you up againſt all this, by repeating to you ſome advantages you poſſeſs; as of Birth, Wit, Goods, Employments; but all this doth not much remove you from Nothing. My deſign is not in the leaſt to offend the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction which Providence it ſelf hath eſtabliſhed, by the Variety of its Adminiſtration; I have a conſideration for Births, Wit, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Employs. But it were to be wiſhed, that thoſe who have theſe Advantages, did not glory in them, and might be throughly perſwaded, that their Elevation doth not raiſe them much above Nothing. Come hither and take a view of him, who is infinitely above you: he was God, and yet was willing to become Man; for this purpoſe he took his Birth from the Womb of a poor and humble Virgin. Be not aſham'd to enter into the Stable where he was born; go thither to learn Humility: For if you don't become like this little Bleſſed Child, <hi>ye ſhall in no wiſe enter into the Kingdom of heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the example of the Birth of our Saviour be not ſufficient to humble you, follow him to <hi>Golgotha,</hi> where you will ſee an example of the moſt Tranſcendent Humility conceivable. When we think of a Crucified Jeſus, we cannot imagine how ſo much Pride ſhould be amongſt Chriſtians: For ſhame let them no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er call themſelves the Diſciples of a Crucified God. Should we judge of the Character of their Maſter, by the Quality of their Manners, we would take him to have been ſome Proud and Self-conceited Philoſopher; whereas indeed he was a Crucified God. Do you ever ſeriouſly conſider this, O ye Chriſtians? You are top-full of Pride, and yet believe that there is no Salvation for you, but by imitating a Maſter, who humbled himſelf to the Death of the Croſs.</p>
            <p>O let us remember for whoſe ſake our Lord hath thus Humbled himſelf, and we ſhall ſee what a model of Charity we have to imitate. 'Tis for men that our Saviour was made Man; 'tis for the Redemption of men, that this God-man died. And pray what are theſe men? Why Duſt and Aſhes, miſerable Sinners. O ſurpaſſing Charity! O Depth of Riches! The Lord God Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and Gracious, abundant in Goodneſs! What ſhall we ſay? No words are able to reach ſuch a Love as this: And indeed God requires actions rather than words, Love for Love; Let us Love God, as he hath Loved us, We cannot do that for him, which he hath done for us; let us Love him, at leaſt with all our ſtrength,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55198:17"/>as he hath Loved us, according to the unbounded largeneſs of his great Compaſſion. Let us Love thoſe whom God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to our Charity; what can we ſay againſt them, that hinders us to exerciſe this Virtue towards them? They have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended us; And what then? Had they done us nothing but Good, it would not be Charity to Love them. Charity conſiſts in this, That we Love our Enemies, as God hath Loved us; us I ſay, that were his Enemies. Let us Forgive, as God Forgives us; exerciſe alſo your Charity in diſtributing to the Poor according to your Ability. God who was Sovereignly Rich, made himſelf Poor for our ſakes. Let us have compaſſion on thoſe Poor which our Lord hath left with us, to prove the Love we bear to him. O the happy <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> this will prove to us, in caſe we can but reſolve to practice Humility and Charity! For after that we ſhall have been made conformable to our Bleſſed Lord by the practice of theſe two Virtues, we ſhall have a ſhare in his Glory, which is the Crown of them. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:55198:17"/>
            <head>The Second Diſcourſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PHILIP. II. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Who being in the Form of God, thought it no Robbery to be equal with God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE know that the Scripture often ſpeaks of God as of man; but it never ſpeaks of man as of God: the reaſon whereof is very evident; for the Divine Nature being wholly Spiritual, it was but neceſſary that the Holy Spirit ſhould clothe it with ſome ſenſible Repreſentations, to the end that entring our Souls by the aſſiſtance of theſe Colours, it might make a deeper impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon them. This is done without any danger, foraſmuch as the Scripture doth elſewhere unfold theſe Metaphors: Or if there be any danger in it with regard to the ſimpler ſort of People, 'tis only this, of falling into an Error which hath no influence upon Divine Worſhip. Hence it is that Scripture makes no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty at all to ſpeak of God as of a man; but never doth it ſpeak of man as of God. For indeed to what purpoſe ſhould this be? So forc'd a Metaphor would be of no uſe at all, and would darken the Stile of the Holy Ghoſt, inſtead of making it more Intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Neither is this the worſt that is in it; for by this means we ſhould be in danger of taking man for God, which is the moſt dangerous of all other miſtakes whatſoever. God is too Jealous of his own Glory, to ſet a Creature on equal ground with Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and he is too much concerned for our Salvation, to put us to the Hazard of ſuch a Miſtake.</p>
            <p>We find alſo, that the Scripture only beſtows very plain encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums upon the very greateſt of men. <hi>Moſes</hi> is an emphatical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55198:18"/>of this; After the Death of that glorious Lawgiver and Commander, all the Panegyrick God beſtows upon him is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd in theſe words, <hi>Moſes my ſervant is dead;</hi> This was enough for a man.<note place="margin">Joſh. 1.2.</note> God took care to hide the Body of this Great Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, for fear they ſhould make a Relick of it. It was thought needful alſo to veil his Glory with an humbling expreſſion, that none might take him for God, but for a Servant of God. From which principle we may without heſitation conclude, That if there be any Being which the Scripture equals with God, that the ſame muſt needs be God. This will be a demonſtrative proof of the Divinity of Chriſt, after we have ſhew'd you, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth all along make him equal with God.</p>
            <p>In our foregoing Diſcourſe we have conſidered this Equality with reference to the Words of the Text only. Our deſign now is to ſhew, that it conſiſts in all thoſe Names, thoſe Attributes, and that Worſhip which belong to the Divine Nature alone, and yet are Communicated to our Saviour. He is ſo call'd, as his Father is; and thus is he equal with God in his Names: He is True God, as his Father; this is his equality in Attributes: He is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured as his Father; and this is his equality as to Worſhip. Follow me in theſe Three Points with your Attention.</p>
            <p>Begin we with the Names; Chriſt, as well as his Father, is called God;<note place="margin">John 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>The word was God:</hi> Neither was it in time that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour received this Name; from the Beginning this Word was God. Let no body tell us here, that the Scripture hath allowed this name to Creatures, as to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and to Magiſtrates: Theſe inſtances are of no force to elude the dint of our Argument from the Name of God Attributed to our Saviour. For is there any thing of parity between examples wherein a glorious Creature is once called God, by way of Compariſon only; and the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the New Teſtament, which ſo often calls Chriſt God by way of perfect Equality? But let us take a nearer view of theſe Examples.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid in <hi>Exodus,</hi> that <hi>Moſes</hi> entring upon his Call, made difficulty to accept of it. God, to determine him to accept of the Commiſſion, told him, <hi>I know that Aaron thy Brother can ſpeak well; he ſhall be thy ſpokeſman unto the People,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 4.14, 16.</note> 
               <hi>and he ſhall be to thee inſtead of a mouth, and thou ſhalt be to him inſtead of God.</hi> That is to ſay, that as God inſpires the Prophets, to inform them what they are
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55198:18"/>to ſay in his Name; in like manner <hi>Moſes</hi> was to communicate his thoughts, or rather thoſe of God to <hi>Aaron,</hi> that ſo <hi>Aaron</hi> might propoſe them to the People. <hi>Moſes</hi> did that with regard to <hi>Aaron,</hi> what God did with reſpect to the Prophets; ſo that <hi>Moſes</hi> was in ſtead of God to <hi>Aaron.</hi> It is not ſimply ſaid, That <hi>Moſes</hi> was God, or that he was the God of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> no nor the God of <hi>Aaron:</hi> far from it; it is only ſaid, that he was in ſtead of a God to <hi>Aaron,</hi> and on this occaſion only. Hath this any the leaſt reſemblance with thoſe places where our Saviour is called God?</p>
            <p>And the ſame may be ſaid of that Text, where it is ſaid, <hi>See, I have made thee a God to Pharaoh, and Aaron thy brother ſhall be thy prophet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 7.1.</note> Theſe words are but the ſequel of the words before explain'd; for if <hi>Moſes</hi> with reference to <hi>Aaron,</hi> diſcharged the place of God, in communicating to him the Oracles of Heaven; it is evident, that <hi>Moſes</hi> diſcharged the ſame Function with reſpect to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> to whom a part of theſe Oracles were ſent. We know, that in the Publication of Oracles, three ſorts of Perſons act their part: God, from whom they originally proceed; the Prophet, whom God commiſſionates therewith; and the Perſon to whom they are addreſt. Whence it appears, that God at the ſame time is the God of the Prophet, by inſpiring him; and the God of the party to whom he cauſeth his will to be declar'd. <hi>Moſes</hi> could not be God with regard to <hi>Aaron,</hi> but he muſt at the ſame time be ſo likewiſe with regard to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> becauſe <hi>Aaron</hi> carried the word of <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> The proof of this Interpretation may be found in that very place, where it is ſaid, <hi>I have made thee a god to Pharaoh;</hi> for it immediately follows, <hi>and Aaron ſhall be thy prophet;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 7.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt ſpeak all that I command thee, and Aaron thy brother ſhall ſpeak unto Pharaoh.</hi> And is it therefore ſaid, That <hi>Moſes</hi> is God ſimply and abſolutely? Not in the leaſt, for this is diſtinctly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited: I have made thee a God for this, that is to ſay, for this only; this is plainly limited. But our Lord is call'd God without the leaſt determination of his Godhead by any Limitations what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; <hi>The word was God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Example of Magiſtrates is not a whit more to the purpoſe, than that of <hi>Moſes.</hi> True it is, that in the 82d <hi>Pſalm</hi> they are called gods; <hi>I have ſaid, ye are gods.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 82</note> This hath nothing common with that way of ſpeaking, wherewith this Name is given to our Saviour. It is not ſaid of any Magiſtrate in particular, that he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55198:19"/>is God; no not ſo much as once throughout all the Scripture. It is only ſaid concerning the Magiſtrates; <hi>Ye are Gods:</hi> That is to ſay, that as Magiſtrates, they are an Image of the Sovereign Judge. So that you ſee, that this alſo is limited, it is not ſaid of any Man, nor of any Angel in particular, and by way of abſolute ſpeaking, that he is God. And yet it is thus that Chriſt is called God. <hi>This Word was God. God hath redeemed his Church with his own blood; God manifeſted in the fleſh.</hi> Nay, what is more; Chriſt is not only called God,<note place="margin">1 John 5.20.</note> but he is called the True God; <hi>This is the true God, and eternal life,</hi> ſaith the Beloved Diſciple. Neither is he only called the True God, but the Great God; for ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiles him;<note place="margin">Tet. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>Looking for the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We cannot but take notice here, that in that ſhort Epiſtle which St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to <hi>Titus,</hi> our Saviour is called God at leaſt four or five times. How comes it to paſs that St. <hi>Paul</hi> in ſo ſhort an <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi> affects to call our Lord ſo often by the Name of God and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour? For it is certain, that as the heavenly Father is God by way of Principle, ſo it is he whom the Scripture commonly calls God; how is it then, I ſay, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> in this ſhort <hi>Epiſtle</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows this Name three or four times upon our Saviour? Without queſtion there was ſome particular Reaſon for it; for any thing I know, it was this, Becauſe the Miniſtry of <hi>Titus</hi> was limited to the Iſle of <hi>Crete.</hi> Now we know this Iſland had a ſingular Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for <hi>Jupiter: Jupiter,</hi> that is to ſay in the Stile of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> The great God, and the Saviour of Men. Many of theſe <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the care of whoſe Souls were committed to <hi>Titus,</hi> had been converted from this Idol to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; that is, to a living and true God. St. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore in oppoſition to the erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Ideas of their Education, beſtows upon Jeſus chriſt theſe very ſame Names in Writing to <hi>Titus.</hi> And this is as much as if he had ſaid to the Chriſtians of that Iſland; <hi>Jupiter</hi> was a Uſurper; he, in whom you have believed, is the only Saviour, and the true God.</p>
            <p>If we had nothing elſe to ſay concerning the Name of God, attributed to our Saviour in the Scripture, we ſhould believe our Argument already very ſtrong, to prove the Divinity of Chriſt. Nothing is call'd God, as he is, but that which is really ſo. He is called God ſimply and abſolutely; and if I may make uſe of an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion popular indeed, but intelligible, I ſay he is called God in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55198:19"/>plain terms, and without ifs, or ands. I make bold to uſe this Expreſſion, that the moſt ſimple may conceive my Meaning, and make the Application themſelves, as they read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>To add more ſtrength to this Argument, we need only to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that the Name of <hi>Jehovah</hi> it ſelf, is given to Jeſus Chriſt in the Scripture. This great Name, this Incommunicable Name, which the <hi>Jews</hi> dare not ſo much as pronounce, ſo worthy do they eſteem it of all reſpect and veneration, is notwithſtanding given to Chriſt; <hi>Ye ſhall not tempt Jehovah your God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>as ye tempted him in Maſſah.</hi> Theſe are the Words of <hi>Moſes.</hi> If we will believe St. <hi>Paul,</hi> our Lord is this <hi>Jehovah</hi> whom the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> tempted; <hi>Neither let us tempt Chriſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as ſome of them alſo tempted.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.9. Iſa. 40.3.</note> 
               <hi>The voice of him that crieth in the wilderneſs, Prepare ye the way of Jehovah.</hi> They are the Words of <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> Let us conſult the Evangeliſts, to know the meaning of them; and they will tell us, That <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> is the Voice crying in the Wilderneſs;<note place="margin">Matt. 3.3. Mark. 1.3. Iſa. 54.5.</note> and that Jeſus Chriſt is that <hi>Jehovah,</hi> whoſe way is prepared; <hi>For thy Maker is thine Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, Jehovah of Hoſts is his name; and thy redeemer the holy one of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael; the God of the whole earth ſhall he be called.</hi> Who is the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom and Husband of the Church? St. <hi>Paul</hi> will inform us:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.2.</note> 
               <hi>I am jealous over you,</hi> ſaith he to the <hi>Corinthians, with a jealouſie of God:</hi> obſerve that Expreſſion, for it was for Chriſt that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was jealous; <hi>For I have eſpouſed you to one Husband, that I may preſent you a chaſt Virgin to Chriſt. I will ſave them by Jehovah their God;</hi> they are the words of God by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Hoſea.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 1.7.</note> By whom is it that the Church is ſaved? Who is it that is our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Redeemer? We know that the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſtly aſſures us in very many places, that it is our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>It would be an eaſy matter to alledge ſeveral other Paſſages out of the Old Teſtament, where the True God is moſt expreſly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, which by the Writers of the New Teſtament are applied to Chriſt. What think we can be the Deſign of theſe Holy Men herein, if Jeſus Chriſt be not indeed that True God? In this caſe I make no difficulty to aſſert, that they have deceived us moſt ſhamefully, and that their Writings are no better than continual Blaſphemies. Pray what is Blaſphemy if this be not, to apply to a Creature what is due to the Creator only; and to appropriate to a meer Man, or even to an Angel, thoſe Oracles which the Holy
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55198:20"/>Ghoſt hath dictated for the Honour of God alone. What a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Opinion is this, the Conſequences whereof turn the Holy Apoſtles into Blaſphemers? As for our part, as long as we ſhall believe that they were not deſtitute of Common Senſe, nor of the Fear of God; as long as we ſhall be perſuaded over and above this, That their Pens were guided by an Infallible Spirit, we muſt be convinced that our Bleſſed Lord, whom they call God, either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, or by application of the Prophetical Paſſages of the Old <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, was God indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Rank of our Proofs reſpects the Equality of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, and furniſheth us with a new Demonſtration in favour of the Godhead of our Saviour. Indeed if we find that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture attributes to our Lord, the very ſame things it appropriates to the Divine Eſſence, will it not be manifeſt that Chriſt is God? What is it to be God, if it be not to have the Nature of God? Now there is nothing that can be more eaſily prov'd, than that our Lord hath the Properties of the Divine Nature, and that in ſuch a manner as belongs to God only. I ſhall make choice of Six of the Divine Attributes, to verifie my Argument: Eternity, Immenſity, Holineſs, Knowledg, Power, and Mercy. The two firſt of theſe Attributes never were, or can be attributed to any created Subſtance; I mean Eternity and Immenſity.</p>
            <p>Having already in a former Diſcourſe, ſpoken of the Eternity of Jeſus Chriſt, it would be uſeleſs to inſiſt any more upon it, were it a Point of leſs conſequence than it is. Upon that account we eſteem it our Duty to enliven your Faith, by quoting the Sacred Author of the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi> In the firſt Chapter he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents them with a ſtrong Motive of perſeverance, by the Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he gives them of the Majeſty of our Lord, whom he raiſeth high above the Angels, and to whom he aſcribes Eternity, by apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Paſſage out of the 102 <hi>Pſalm</hi> to him;<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>They</hi> (the Heavens) <hi>ſhall periſh, but thou ſhalt endure; yea, all of them ſhall wax old like a garment; as a veſture ſhalt thou change them, and they ſhall be changed; but thou art the ſame, and thy years ſhall have no end.</hi> To underſtand the true ſenſe of this Oracle, we muſt ſearch for it at the Fountain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, I mean, in the <hi>Pſalm</hi> if ſelf; where we ſhall find it plainly ſignifies the Eternity of the Divine Nature; not only Eternity to come, but alſo that which is paſt. We do not find that the Sacred Author hath added the leaſt reſtriction to the words of the Text, but attributes them in their whole and entire ſtrength to Jeſus
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55198:20"/>Chriſt. Our Saviour therefore is Eternal, with regard to both ſides of Eternity.</p>
            <p>In runing over this <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> we cannot ſilently paſs over an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument the Author inſiſts upon in the Third <hi>Chapter,</hi> to confirm Chriſtians in their Perſeverance, by the Advantages which raiſe Chriſt far above <hi>Moſes: For this perſon was counted worthy of more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry than Moſes; in as much as he who hath built the houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>hath more honour than the houſe.</hi> This way of reaſoning amounts to nothing, if it do not ſuppoſe our Saviour to be the Builder of the Houſe. <hi>But,</hi> ſaith the Author in the Verſe following, <hi>He that built all things, is God;</hi> Jeſus Chriſt therefore is God: Nevertheleſs it appears, that the Father alſo is the Builder of the Houſe; for it is ſaid, that Chriſt, as Son, is over the Houſe of God. But this is eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd; for the Father and the Son poſſeſſing one and the ſame Nature, the one is ſuppos'd to have done what the other did.</p>
            <p>Proceed we to the ſeventh Chapter, where we meet with an Emphatical Proof of the Eternity of Chriſt. The Apoſtle there teacheth us, that <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> is the true Portraiture of our Lord; in this Type I find a <hi>King of righteouſneſs, and of Peace;</hi> and ſo far the Reſemblance is exact: for we know that Righteouſneſs and Peace kiſs and embrace each other in the Original. But conſider we thoſe other Lineaments that compoſe the Type; <hi>He was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Father, without Mother, without deſcent, having neither beginning of days, nor end of life.</hi> This, according to the Letter, cannot be ſaid of any Man: if <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> was a Man, he had Father, Mother, Deſcent, beginning of Days, and end of Life; but nothing of all this is found in the Scripture, where not the leaſt mention is made of the Family, nor of the Birth, nor of the Death of <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> which is very ſtrange; foraſmuch as the Holy Ghoſt hath given us the <hi>Genealogy</hi> of many Perſons much leſs conſiderable, how comes it to paſs that it hath neglected to give us theſe particulars concerning the great <hi>Melchiſedec?</hi> Why the reaſon is plain; his Deſign was to repreſent to us a Portraiture that might reſemble our Lord; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made like the Son of God,</hi> ſaith our Author. The Holy Ghoſt on purpoſe ſuppreſſeth the Birth and Death of <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> to the end that this Illuſtrious, Unknown, might the better repreſent the Eternity of the Son of God, who is <hi>without beginning of days, as he is without end of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:55198:21"/>
            <p>In the <hi>9th Chapter</hi> we find a new Proof of the Eternity of our Saviour.<note place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> It is ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt through the eternal ſpirit, offered himſelf to God;</hi> What is this Eternal Spirit here mention'd? It is not the Soul of our Lord that is now here called the Eternal Spirit. Beſides, the Soul of our Lord was a part of the Sacrifice it ſelf; whereas the words ſpeak of the Nature that offers, and not of that which is offer'd. Neither is it the Holy Ghoſt, the Third Perſon in the Sacred Trinity; he did not offer up our Saviour, but he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd up himſelf; it muſt therefore have been an other Nature, which our Saviour here calls the Eternal Spirit. The Godhead of Chriſt perform'd the Prieſt's Office here upon the Manhood, prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated to be the Victim for Mankind.</p>
            <p>I refer alſo to this, That Argument which the ſame Author draws from the Eternity of Jeſus Chriſt, to engage the Chriſtians to perſevere in his Doctrine; <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever.</hi> The Apoſtle by theſe words renews the Notion he had given them in the beginning of this Epiſtle; where we have ſeen, that he aſſerts the Eternity of Jeſus Chriſt from a Text of the <hi>Old Teſtamnnt.</hi> Indeed we find the Author had this Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his eye, throughout, to the very end of the <hi>Epiſtle;</hi> and 'tis with reference to this, that we muſt explain this Elogy of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, which comprehends all diſtinction of Time paſt, preſent, and to come: <hi>He is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever:</hi> which anſwers to the Explication St. <hi>John</hi> gives us of the Eternity of the Father: <hi>Grace be unto you, and peace, from him which is, and which was,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>and which is to come.</hi> And the very ſame Expreſſion is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Chriſt by St. <hi>John;</hi> or rather our Saviour attributes it to himſelf, in St. <hi>John</hi>'s Revelation:<note place="margin">Rev. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>I am Alpha avd Omega, the Beginning and the End, ſaith the Lord, which is, which was, and which is to come, the Almighty.</hi> Who is it that ſpeaks thus? He of whom it is ſaid in the verſe foregoing, <hi>Behold he cometh with clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him:</hi> is the ſame, who in the following Verſe ſaith, <hi>I am Alpha and Omega, the firſt and the laſt:</hi> For St. <hi>John</hi> having turned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſee who it was whoſe Voice he heard, ſaw Jeſus Chriſt. Our Lord therefore is Eternal.</p>
            <p>Immenſity is the Second Attribute, by which our Saviour is preſent in all places at the ſame time. If it were not ſo, how could he make good the Promiſe made to his Diſciples: <hi>For where two or three are gathered together in my name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>there am I in the midſt of them.</hi> It is very obſervable, that this is the Language of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55198:21"/>the Old Law, where we ſee, that in ſeveral paſſages he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to dwell amidſt his People. Think we that any one but the Son druſt have ſpoke like the Father? Beſides, I will take the boldneſs to ſay, that as Grace diſplays it ſelf in the Goſpel, the Son by promiſing his preſence in all places, ſaith yet more than the Father. The Father aſſures his People that he will dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and ſometimes does even reſtrain this his Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the compaſs of the Tabernacle. <hi>They ſhall make me a Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> ſaith he, in <hi>Exodus, and I will dwell in the midſt of them.</hi> But our Saviour extends his Promiſe to a much greater compaſs, even to a <hi>whereſoever two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midſt of them.</hi> As if he had ſaid, That place whereſoever it be, ſhall be to me a <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> a Tabernacle, a Sanctuary. What can this import leſs than Immenſity, at a time when Grace over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flows the whole Univerſe, without any diſtinction of People? In all parts of the World our Lord is preſent in the midſt of the leaſt Aſſemblies, where his Name is called upon. He is in all places at the ſame time, he ſees what is done there, he hears all that is ſaid there, he bleſſeth thoſe whom he will bleſs: In a word, he is in all places where he is call'd upon, as God was in the Sanctuary of old. It is well enough known, that when our Saviour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth his preſence, he means a preſence of his Virtue and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences. Immenſity is not the proper ſubject of a Promiſe. That which of its own Nature is preſent in all places, is there, whether he promiſe it or not; but becauſe our Lord doth promiſe a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Virtue in all places, we have good reaſon to conclude that he is in all places. This Concluſion is evident, our Saviour could not act in all places, if he were not in all places.</p>
            <p>Now-a-days 'tis maintain'd, that we cannot conceive the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of God in any place, but by ſome Divine Operations. God is every where, ſay they, becauſe he operates every where. Say we the ſame of our Saviour, he is every where, becauſe he acts every where: <hi>For where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midſt of them.</hi> We need no more than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe to convince us, that if our Bleſſed Lord had no other Amplitude but that of his Human Nature, he could never fulfil this great Promiſe. But ſtill to open a further Light to his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſity, we need only call to mind his Diſcourſe with <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> in the third of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel; <hi>No man hath aſcended up to heaven, but hothat came down from heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>even the Son of Man which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55198:22"/>is in heaven.</hi> He is diſcourſing with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> here on Earth, and at the ſame time tells him he is in Heaven. This can admit of no tolerable explication, but by means of that Immenſity whereby he <hi>fills heaven and earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the two Divine Attributes that are abſolutely incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable to Creatures. Let us next run over the other Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, that are by ſome way of Analogy communicable to them, but are poſſeſt by God in the higheſt degree of Abſoluteneſs and Perfection. I ſhall not ſay that our Saviour is Holy, that he is Intelligent, that he is Powerful and Merciful; which are the four Attributes that remain to be examined. Should we ſay no more than ſo, all this may be attributed to Creatures. We find amongſt them Holineſs, Knowledge, Power and Mercy. No bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy can doubt, but that if we make it evident that our Lord poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth all theſe four Perfections as God doth, you will be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd with as many Demonſtrations to evince the Divinity of our Saviour.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour then is Holy, but ſo as God is, which we prove from a plain Text of Scripture. The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> tells us in his ſixth Chapter, that he <hi>ſaw the Lord ſitting upon a throne,</hi> amidſt the Acclamations of the Seraphims, who cried one to another, and ſaid, <hi>Holy, holy, holy, is the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> Would you know who this Lord, or rather <hi>Jehovah,</hi> is, to whom they give the threefold Compellation of Holy? St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve you; who tells us in the twelfth Chapter of his Goſpel, that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpake of our Saviour.<note place="margin">Joh. 12, 41.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe things ſaid Eſaias, when he ſaw his glory, and ſpake of him.</hi> Some have been of Opinion, that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was condemn'd to Death, becauſe he had preſum'd to ſay, That he had <hi>ſeen him who was inviſible.</hi> This ſeem'd to be a meer piece of Blaſphemy; but what can be imagin'd more abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than that which St. <hi>John</hi> tells us here, if our Bleſſed Lord be not indeed the King, the Lord of Hoſts, the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Let us make no ſcruple to believe the Beloved Diſciple, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd himſelf on the Breaſt of the Son of God: Truſt we the piercing ſight of this Eagle, who took ſo near a view of this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Son? Rely we upon the Teſtimony of an Evangeliſt, whoſe end in writing his Goſpel, was to prove that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God. It is he aſſures us, that he whom the Seraphims with ſo much Humility adore, crying to one another, and ſaying, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55198:22"/>holy, holy is the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> was no other than our Bleſſed Lord.</p>
            <p>We ſay further, That he hath Knowledge alſo, but as God. He knows all that God knows: Remember always that we ſpeak of the Son of God. We know that the Son of Man had a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which encreas'd by degrees, and what is more, that he did not know all things: <hi>No man knows that hour,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>no not the Son of Man.</hi> This is true of the Son of Man, or of the Human Nature of our Saviour; but the Son of God, the Divine Nature in our Saviour, knew that which the Son of Man knew not. The Son of God knows all that God knows, that is all things: St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us as much; <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou knoweſt all things, thou knoweſt that I love thee.</hi> This Knowledge is Univerſal; and to take a view of it that way, where with one caſt of the Eye, you may diſcover it to be the Knowledge of God; we need only to obſerve, that the Eyes of our Lord pierce to the very bottom of Man's Heart. <hi>Thou knoweſt all things, thou knoweſt that I love thee.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Heart was not the only Heart that was known to Chriſt: <hi>All things were naked and open before him; Lord, thou knoweſt all things.</hi> The Propoſition is general. The Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, thoſe Hypocritical Profeſſors, could not hide their moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Thoughts from him; this Truth appears from many paſſages of the Goſpel. To Cite only one place, which by reaſon of its generality, comprehends all the reſt; we need only take notice of what St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith towards the end of the Second Chapter of his Goſpel: <hi>But Jeſus did not commit himſelf unto them,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Joh. 2.24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knew all men, and needed not that any ſhould teſtifie of man; for he knew what was in man.</hi> The Caſe here mentioned is not that of a Prophet, to whom God diſcovers the Heart of ſome particular Man. The Knowledge which the Goſpel aſcribes to our Saviour is Univerſal, no Heart eſcapes him. <hi>He knew what was in man.</hi> A Knowledge that God in a moſt peculiar manner appropriates to himſelf in ſeveral places of the Old Teſtament. <hi>I know, my God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 29.17. Jerem. 17.10.</note> 
               <hi>that thou trieſt the heart,</hi> ſaid <hi>David</hi> towards the latter end of his Life. <hi>I the Lord ſearch the heart, I try the reins,</hi> ſaith he himſelf by the Mouth of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy.</hi> Let us read to the end of the Verſe; <hi>Even,</hi> continues he, <hi>to give to every man according to his ways, and according to the fruit of his doings.</hi> 'Tis God that ſpeaks here, and he ſpeaks as God; he ſpeaks like himſelf. Never did any Prophet ſpeak thus. And yet this is the very paſſage our
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55198:23"/>Lord aſcribes to himſelf in the Revelation, ſpeaking to the Angel of the Church of <hi>Thyatira;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2.23.</note> 
               <hi>And all the Churches ſhall know that I am he which ſearches the reins and hearts; and I will give unto every one of you according to your works.</hi> Words that make it evident, that our Saviour declares expreſly, that it was himſelf that ſpake in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy,</hi> and that the Knowledge of the Heart of Man belongs to him in chief.</p>
            <p>The Fifth Attribute whereby we learn to know the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſt, is his Power, He is powerful, but ſo as to be powerful as God; he is the Almighty. In Virtue of this power, the Son doth all that the Father doth.<note place="margin">Joh. 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>What things ſoever the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth, theſe alſo doth the Son likewiſe.</hi> Doth the Father raiſe the Dead! So doth the Son alſo, <hi>he quickneth whom he will.</hi> Doth the Father create the World? The Son doth ſo likewiſe. Which two inſtances ſhew us the extent of the Father's Power: Indeed we cannot conceive any greater, than that of reſtoring Life to the Dead, and that of creating ſuch a World as this is, and yet both theſe belong to our Saviour.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, he hath raiſed the Dead; but have not others done the ſame Miracle? <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Eliſha</hi> in the Old Teſtament; and the Diſciples of our Lord in the New, have not they alſo raiſed ſome that were Dead, who for all that, never pretended to be equal with God. True it is, that <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Eliſha</hi> each of them raiſed a Child to Life, but with what pains do they work theſe Miracles? God makes them ſweat for it, that it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that theſe Saints were but Men. <hi>Elijah ſtretcheth himſelf upon the child three ſeveral times, and cries to the Lord. Eliſha</hi> not being able to do any thing by the Miniſtry of his Servant, comes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the room where the Child was. The Prophet lyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Child, and puts his Mouth to the Childs Mouth, and his Eyes upon the Childs Eyes, and his Hands upon the Childs Hands, trying to reſtore Life and Heat to the Child; but for all this the deſired Effect doth not follow; he goes up and comes down, and after having ſeveral times ſtretched himſelf upon the Child, at laſt by the Bleſſing of God, the Child begins to ſhew ſome ſigns of Life. Was this the way our Saviour took to raiſe the Dead? Being touched with Compaſſion for the Widow of <hi>Naim,</hi> whoſe only Son was carried forth to be buried, our Saviour ſaith to the Dead,<note place="margin">Mar. 5.41.</note> 
               <hi>Young Man ariſe;</hi> and that word did the thing without any more ado; neither ſaid he more in raiſing to Life the Daughter
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55198:23"/>of the Ruler of the Synagogue, but <hi>Damſel ariſe;</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> was raiſed with this word, <hi>Lazarus come forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no need to inſiſt upon the Reſurrections wrought by the Diſciples of our Lord, for they being performed in his Name, were to be attributed only to the Efficacy of his Virtue. Beſides theſe particular Reſurrections which prove the Omnipotence of our Lord, we ought alſo to conſider that he attributes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Reſurrection of all Believers. All he did here upon Earth was but a Scantling of what he ſhall do one day, by command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Death to give up her dead, after that their diſſipated Duſt hath been carried by the Wind to the utmoſt Corners of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. <hi>He that believes in me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hath eternal life, and I will raiſe him at the laſt day.</hi> Is this the Stile of a Creature? Purſuant to this Promiſe, ſeveral times repeated in the Goſpel, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> as if he would prove to them, that Chriſt is equal to God his Father, that Jeſus Chriſt ſhall change our vile Bodies, and make them conform alſo to his glorious Body, <hi>by that power whereby he is able, even to ſubdue all things to himſelf.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> See here the Omnipotence of our Saviour expreſt with the greateſt plainneſs that may be.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, I aſſerted that Chriſt had created the World. He hath created all that we ſee, and all that we do not ſee, for he is the Creator both of Angels and Men, the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of all things; <hi>without him nothing was made that was made.</hi> Let us make uſe of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Expreſſions; <hi>For by him were all things created, that are in heaven, and that are in earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>viſible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible; whether they be thrones or dominions, or principalities, or powers, all things were created by him, and for him.</hi> Theſe words are ſo full and ſtrong, and are alone ſufficient to prove that our Lord is equal in power with his Father.</p>
            <p>The laſt Attribute wherewith we evince the equality which St. <hi>Paul</hi> attributes to our Saviour, or rather which our Saviour attributes to himſelf, is that of Mercy. We can no ſooner have any little knowledge of the Myſtery of our Redemption by Jeſus Chriſt, but we muſt acknowledge that our Redeemer is merciful, in a manner that doth not belong to any but God. Was it not he himſelf, think we, to whom <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Lord, the Lord God, merciful and gracious.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 33. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34.</note> This great Lawgiver had a deſire to ſee God; <hi>I beſeech thee,</hi> ſaid <hi>Moſes, ſhew me thy glory;</hi> and God's anſwer was, <hi>I will make all my goodneſs paſs before thee;</hi> where by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55198:24"/>the way we may obſerve to our great comfort, that the Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates to us, that his Goodneſs is his great Glory. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he informs <hi>Moſes,</hi> that no Man can look God in the Face: <hi>Thou ſhalt ſee my back parts,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>but my face ſhall not be ſeen.</hi> What may be the meaning of this Expreſſion? The Interpreters are generally agreed, that this ſignifies, that God cannot be ſeen but by and in his Works; and that the Myſterious Reaſons of his Conduct are not diſcerned. Thus far this Explication is plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough; but yet this is not enough, except they comprehend in theſe his Works, the Works of Grace. Indeed thoſe are chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here intended; <hi>I will make all my goodneſs paſs before thee.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I pray, conſiſts all the goodneſs of God? Why, it is all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centred in the Myſtery of the Death of Chriſt. When <hi>Moſes</hi> had a glimpſe of this Infinite Goodneſs, when the Crucified Jeſus was pourtray'd before the Eyes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> then it was that he cry'd out, ſaying, <hi>The Lord, the Lord God, merciful and gracious, long ſuffering, and abundant in goodneſs and truth.</hi> And indeed, who would not do as much, at the view, (tho a diſtant one) of the Mercy of the Son of God, <hi>who being in the Form of God,</hi> never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs emptied himſelf. Chriſt's Mercy alone is ſufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate him to be the true God.</p>
            <p>God only is good in that manner, becauſe he who ſaid to our Lord, <hi>Good maſter what ſhall I do to have eternal life;</hi> did not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend this Truth. Our Lord ſaith to him, <hi>Why calleſt thou me good? There is none good but God;</hi> thou who doſt not know that I am God, why doſt thou call me good? Yet our Lord, who very well knew his own Rights, gives himſelf that Title, <hi>I am the good ſhepherd,</hi> ſaith he in the Tenth Chapter of St. <hi>John;</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Principle of our Saviour himſelf, it might have been told him, Why doſt thou call thy ſelf good, <hi>there is none good but God;</hi> but knowing very well what he was, he made himſelf equal with God in goodneſs.</p>
            <p>The whole Goſpel is full of the Traces of that Mercy, which our Saviour hath exerciſed in chief. You have already ſeen this, in that he pardons ſins, not as Miniſters do, by way of Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but as God, by an abſolute and independent Authority. The manner of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s wiſhing Grace, is alſo an evident proof of this Truth: <hi>Grace be unto you, and peace from God our father, and from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This is the common Seal of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, by which he renders an Authentick Witneſs to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55198:24"/>Divinity. The Chriſtians who had been Educated in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion, and thereby accuſtomed to hear nothing more frequently ſpoken of than the Bleſſing, the Peace, and the Grace of God, could not underſtand it otherwiſe. An Apoſtle would have been better advis'd than to wiſh them Grace proceeding elſewhere than from God. This Grace alone is ſufficient for us. The Scripture never tell us of the Grace of Angels, or of Men. Where is there any mention made in form of wiſhing the Grace of <hi>Abraham,</hi> or that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or St. <hi>Peter,</hi> or St. <hi>Paul?</hi> The Church lives only by the Grace of God; inſomuch that this Salutation, <hi>The grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you,</hi> is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent proof of the Divinity of our Great Redeemer. He is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as you ſee, equal to his Father in Eternity, in Immenſity, in Holineſs, in Power, and in Mercy. And what is the reſult of this Equality but this, that our Lord poſſeſſeth the Attributes of the Divine Eſſence, and enjoys the Honour that is inconteſtably due to that Eſſence? This is the third Head whereby we prove, that Jeſus Chriſt is equal with his Father.</p>
            <p>That which at firſt put us upon the Meditation of this Article, is that Honourable Rank our Saviour holds in the Scriptures. In that Sacred Book where every thing is in its proper place, and where nothing that is created, is made to go hand in hand with God; and yet there we ever ſee the Son always join'd with his Heavenly Father; <hi>Teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt. There are three that bear record in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 5.7.</note> Theſe are Texts where we ſee theſe three Adorable Perſons rank'd in one Line. St. <hi>Paul</hi> bleſſeth the <hi>Corinthians</hi> from the Son, even as from the Father. <hi>The grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the love of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>and the communion of the Holy Ghoſt be with you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A remarkable paſſage indeed, where we find the Son even nam'd before the Father, which yet we find alſo in many other paſſages. But why is the order here inverted? To make it appear,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.1, 2. 2 Theſ. 2.16.</note> ſay the Fathers, that the order of names does not import a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination of different Natures. The Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, are only one Divine Nature; and therefore it is that the Scripture ſometimes placeth the Son above the Father. Can we imagine that that Sacred Record would ever have committed ſuch an abſurdity, if the Son had been no more than a Creature? I appeal to any Man, who hath in the leaſt degree ſavour'd the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55198:25"/>of Scripture. What think we of ſuch a ſpeech as this, The Grace of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Love of God be with you all? Or of this, <hi>Joſhua,</hi> call'd to be a Leader of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not of Men, nor by Man, but by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 1.1.</note> and by God; or of this, Now <hi>Moſes</hi> and God comfort your Hearts. I appeal to any one, whether it be not prophane to talk at this rate; and yet do but put the Name of Jeſus Chriſt inſtead of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and we ſhall find all theſe paſſages word for word in the New Teſtament. This is an obſervation rais'd from the Son's being ſometimes named before the Father; but tho the Son had been continually plac'd in the ſecond rank, as indeed commonly he is, yet the Argument for all that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues in its full force. The Son would never have been join'd with the Father in the Scripture, if the Son had been a Creature, becauſe he would have been infinitely inferior to him; neither would the Scripture ever have ſuppreſs'd this diſtance, by rang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Father and the Son together in one Line, and placing them on one and the ſame Throne. Is not this to tell us plainly and openly, that both of them poſſeſs the ſame undivided Nature? This is the Honour the Holy Ghoſt hath given to the Son of God in the Scriptures. See we now what Honour we Men ought to render to this Son, who is our Maſter and Saviour.</p>
            <p>Worſhip is as it were the ſhadow of the Godhead, let us thereby take the height and elevation of the Lord we are to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. To this purpoſe let us lay this down for a Principle, That the Glory of Adoration belongs to none but God alone. Should I go about to prove this Truth from the Old Teſtament, I ſhould be fain to take in the Teſtimony of all the Prophets. They have all of them in the moſt ſmart and lively terms expreſs'd the Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie of God, for any Divine Honours exhibited to Creatures. We need but caſt our Eyes upon the Old Teſtament to be fully convinc'd thereof. It being indeed no other than a perpetual Commentary upon the Firſt Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me.</hi> There never was any the leaſt variation or conteſt in this point. Never did the Prophets patiently endure to ſee Men worſhip any other gods, ſave him alone who hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Heaven and Earth. Theſe Holy Men unanimouſly declare, that to him alone belongs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Glory of Adoration. No Creature at all is to be worſhipp'd, neither Stars, nor Plants, nor living Creatures, nor Men, nor Angels. Men indeed have ſometimes been called gods, as we have already taken notice. <hi>Moſes</hi> was
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55198:25"/>inſtead of God to <hi>Aaron;</hi> and Judges are called gods; we alſo find this name given to Angels in ſome places; but this name given by way of Metaphor doth not import Adoration; <hi>Aaron</hi> did not adore <hi>Moſes;</hi> neither did <hi>Iſrael</hi> adore their Judges, or the Angels; for this is the glory of God only, and he hath ſworn he will not give his glory to another.</p>
            <p>Neither hath this point of Divinity been alter'd under the New Teſtament. It is none of thoſe Moſaick Rites, that were to ceaſe as ſoon as the fulneſs of time was come. God is always God; and if we may ſo ſay, he never was more God, than he is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; or to ſoften the Expreſſion, he never more appear'd God than in the Manifeſtation of Grace. Herein he hath made all his Goodneſs to paſs before us, and conſequently he never more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to be only worſhipped. Shall we ſuppoſe then, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Diſpenſation, where by a new Effuſion of Grace he hath deſerved an acceſſion to his former glory of Adoration, that he is become unconcern'd for that glory, whereof formerly he was ſo Jealous? And to that degree, as to ſet a Creature at his Right Hand? A Creature plac'd on God's ſide, is ſomething that is contradictory: Let us ſet every thing in its proper place. God always abides alone in the Throne, and the Creature at the foot of it.</p>
            <p>But without having recourſe to Reaſoning, which inform us that the glory of God, is an unalienable Right and Poſſeſſion; the Holy Scripture aſſures us, that under the Goſpel, as well as under the Law, the glory of Religious worſhip belongs to God only. We know the anſwer our Lord return'd to a Creature that would fain have been ador'd; <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him alone ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> This anſwer is good at all times. The Apoſtles uſe the ſame Language as their Maſter; they ſay in more places than one,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.17. Rom. 16.27. Acts 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>To the only wiſe God be honour and glory for ever and ever, Amen.</hi> When St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſees Men about to worſhip the Creature, he points them ſtraight to the Living God; <hi>We preach unto you, that ye ſhould turn from theſe vanities to the living God.</hi> 'Tis to him alone that your Homage of right is due. When the Apoſtle repreſents to the <hi>Galatians</hi> the exceſs of that Corruption wherewith they were infected before their Converſion;<note place="margin">Gal. 4.8.</note> he tells them they <hi>ſerved thoſe things which by nature were no gods.</hi> It is then, according to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Judgment, a great Sin to ſerve that which is not God by Nature. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:55198:26"/>I find, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> obligeth me to worſhip any Being; I may have good reaſon, according to the Opinion we have of him, to conclude, That this Adorable Being is God, and God too by his Nature. For it is not lawful for us to worſhip any Being, ſave God alone. Let us learn this from the <hi>Revelations;</hi> that Book wherewith the Holy Ghoſt hath been pleaſed, as it were, to ſeal up the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> He that preacheth this Doctrine, is an Angel; one of thoſe Spirits that are well inform'd how things are carried in Heaven; I ſay it is an Angel that teacheth us, that God alone is to be worſhipped.<note place="margin">Rev. 22.9.</note> St. <hi>John</hi> falls down to worſhip before the feet of the Angel, <hi>See thou do it not,</hi> ſaith he: And why not? <hi>for,</hi> adds he, <hi>I am thy fellow ſervant.</hi> Conclude we then; That whatſoever is bound to worſhip God, cannot be an Object of Adoration. Who then is it that we are to adore? <hi>Worſhip God,</hi> ſaith the Angel. God only deſerves the honour of Adoration under the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as well as under the <hi>Old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no ſolid Reaſoning in the world, if after having eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed this Principle, I may not conclude thence, that our Bleſſed Saviour is God, with reſpect to one of his Natures, ſeeing the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel makes it our Duty to worſhip him. Will it be neceſſary to prove that this Adoration is a Worſhip practis'd and preſcrib'd by the <hi>Apoſtles?</hi> Why we need but open the Books of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and we ſhall meet with the Proof of it; You will ſee the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves, and many other Believers, worſhiping the Lord, without the leaſt check from him, or ſaying to them, <hi>See thou do it not.</hi> Let none wrangle here about the Word Adoration. They take Jeſus Chriſt for the Son of God, and they adore him under that Notion. He hath never rejected, or diſowned this Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but hath received it as a Tribute due unto him.</p>
            <p>We meet with a Character in the Stile of Sacred Authors, which puts the Divine Adoration we owe to our Saviour, out of the reach of any manner of Contradiction. They are wont to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt their Stile by Doxologies to the Honour of God. And the ſame they do to our Saviour, and in the ſame Terms, and that in ſeveral places.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.11. Rev. 1.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>That God in all things may be glorified, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be praiſe and dominion for ever and ever. Amen.</hi> They are the words of St. <hi>Peter: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto him that loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood, and hath made us kings and prieſts unto God, even his Father; to him be glory and dominion for ever and ever. Amen:</hi> As St. <hi>John</hi> expreſſeth himſelf in the beginning of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55198:26"/>What are we to conclude from hence, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> make uſe of theſe kind of <hi>Doxologies</hi> to the honour of Jeſus, but this, That he is truly equal with his Father, and that they honour him after one and the ſame manner? Purſue we this Point a little farther, and examine more particularly wherein this Adoration doth conſiſt, that ſo we may be the better inform'd what the Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of his Divine Nature is.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Chapter</hi> that hath furniſh'd us with our <hi>Text,</hi> we ſee that our Lord hath <hi>a Name above every Name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>that at the Name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow, of things in heaven, and things in earth, and things under the earth.</hi> Thus it is that the <hi>Scripture</hi> Language expreſſeth the whole Univerſe of things: All things muſt bend the Knee to Jeſus, which yet is not to be underſtood of thoſe five Letters, as if that Name did merit a more ſingular veneration, than the other Names of our Saviour. The Cuſtom which hath been introduc'd of bowing themſelves at the pronunciation of the Name of Jeſus, is not founded upon theſe words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> but only becauſe the Chriſtians thought it neceſſary to make this Mark of Reſpect, the Teſt of their Belief in his Divinity. So that indeed it is to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that we owe the honour of Genuflexion. Every thing muſt bow before our Lord; <hi>He hath received a Name above every Name, that at the Name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have an excellent Explication of thoſe words in thoſe Paſſages of <hi>Scripture,</hi> where we ſee that in our <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> all things muſt be done in the Name of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> Nothing can be imagin'd greater than this Honour: <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are baptized in this Name; they believe in this Name; they work Miracles in this Name; they are juſtified in this Name; they meet together in this Name; they pronounce their Deliberations in this Name; they preach in this Name; they ſuffer for this Name; they pray in this Name; they return Thanks in this Name; and in one word, to make uſe of the words of St. <hi>Paul, Whatſoever they do in word or deed, they do all in the Name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> I demand therefore, Whether ever any Creature was thus glorified in <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Is it not notorious that the Name of God only, was named amongſt that People? no other Name was heard of amongſt them in their Church, but the Name of God only: They did not ſwear, but by the Name of God; they did not bleſs, but in the Name of God; they heard of no Deliverances, but in the Name of God; they glorified no other Name but that of God only. What therefore muſt we conclude him to be, whoſe Name
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55198:27"/>muſt be celebrated under the New Covenant; that is, throughout all the Earth, as the Name of God was under the Old Covenant; that is to ſay, in a very ſmall Corner of the World? The Father allows the Son to be glorified more than he himſelf hath been; as it were to make an amends to the Son for his Subordination, under which he appears with regard to the Father. Whatever it be, the Name of the Son holds a Sovereigh Rank, and not that of a Prophet or Ambaſſador. Theſe Deputies do all things in the Name of the Sovereign who hath deputed them, not in their own. Wherefore, ſince the Name of Chriſt is made uſe of every where, it is an unconteſtable Mark that he is Maſter, that he is King, that he is Sovereign; yea, that he is God bleſſed for ever. Let no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy reply here, That all this was done in time. I am not afraid to aſſert, God can conſtitute no Sovereign in his Church, becauſe in doing ſo, he muſt renounce the unalienable Right of his Nature, which admits no Peer, neither in Heaven, nor on Earth: But the Name of Jeſus Chriſt hath been thus elevated, becauſe according to one of his Natures he is the Son. This is a Myſtery he himſelf o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to us; when after having ſaid in the 11th Chapter of St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 11.27.</note> 
               <hi>All things are delivered unto me of my Father;</hi> he adds, to ſhew that he had received this Power becauſe he was the Eternal Son of God, <hi>And no man knoweth the Son but the Father; neither knoweth any man the Father ſave the Son.</hi> We ſhall have occaſion once more to ſpeak of this matter. But we proceed now to a more particular enquiry, wherein the Worſhip we owe to Jeſus Chriſt our Lord doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
            <p>There is no queſtion but that <hi>Genuflexion,</hi> and bowing of the Body, are comprehended in the ſenſe of theſe words; but they extend yet further; they ſignifie all the Worſhip we owe to the Godhead. This is the Signification they have in the Prophets whence they are taken; <hi>I have ſworn by my ſelf, that unto me every knee ſhall bow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 45.23.</note> ſaith God by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> All the kinds of Adoration are expreſs'd in this manner of ſpeaking; Proſtration of the Body, humiliation of Soul, and even the total Annihilati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Man: All this is due to our Lord. I will not inſiſt upon the Bowing, or Proſtration of the Body, becauſe that is the leaſt part of Worſhip, and to ſpeak properly, is no more than a ſign, and a variable one too, of the true Adoration; for we may adore without kneeling. The Church of old prayed ſtanding for ſome time. So that we ſhall add no more concerning the Adoration of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:55198:27"/>the Body, ſave only this, that we owe our Body to Jeſus Chriſt, as to that God who hath created it.</p>
            <p>As for the Soul, which is the true Principle of Worſhip, let us conceive all the ways whereby it is capable of adoring God, all theſe ſhe owes to our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. This is that we muſt prove by Scripture, that we may not aſſert any thing with relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this Myſtery, without the information of this Infallible Guide. Sacrifice, and Truſt or Confidence, honour God as Sovereign. In Sacrifice we offer all to God; in Truſt and Confidence we expect all from him. Under the Old Law God reſerv'd this dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Honour to himſelf; there was no Sacrificing, but to him, no truſting or confiding, but in him. All this is transferr'd to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. As to Sacrifice, we cannot now look for any other than that of Prayer, ſince the time of Bloody Sacrifices is ceaſed. The Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Prayer is much more worthy of God, than the Blood of the Ancient Sacrifices. This new Sacrifice we owe to our Lord. St. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> dies, after having offer'd up this Sacrifice to our Saviour; <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my Spirit,</hi> cry'd that firſt Martyr. It was with this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice that St. <hi>Paul</hi> began his Chriſtian Race: For <hi>Ananias</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring to him what he was to do, in order to obey him who had ſtopt him on his way to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Acts 11.16.</note> 
               <hi>Why tarrieſt thou? ariſe, and be baptized, and waſh away thy ſins, by calling on the name of the Lord.</hi> The entrance of the Proſelites into the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church was by Circumciſion, by Baptiſm, and by Sacrifice. Circumciſion was now ceaſed; ſo that there remained nothing neceſſary for St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s admittance, but Baptiſm and Sacrifice; and accordingly he is bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and for his Sacrifice he calls upon the Name of the Lord. This piece of Worſhip is ſo eſſential to Chriſtianity, that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are deſcribed in ſeveral places, by thoſe that call upon the Name of the Lord. The time is come, that <hi>whoſoever calls on the name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaved:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.21. Joel 2.31. 1 Cor. 1.2.</note> Words quoted from the Prophet <hi>Joel,</hi> and apply'd to our Saviour. In <hi>Joel</hi> they plainly belong to God: And what did St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> think of, when they apply'd them to our Lord, if he be not God? St. <hi>Peter</hi> upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the <hi>Pentecoſtal</hi> Miracle, ſaith, that that was a fulfilling of the words of <hi>Joel:</hi> And St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to ſhew the neceſſity of the preaching of the Goſpel, grounds his Diſcourſe upon theſe words: <hi>Whoſoever ſhall call upon the name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>How then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhall they call upon him, in whom they have not believed? And how ſhall they believe in him, of whom they have not heard? And how
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55198:28"/>ſhall they hear without a Preacher?</hi> This therefore ſhews at the ſame time, that we are to call upon Jeſus Chriſt, and to call upon him as God.</p>
            <p>Confidence or Truſt is the Second Branch of Divine Worſhip. God, and God alone, was the Hope of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Hope of <hi>David,</hi> the Hope of all the Saints under the Old Law. Not becauſe God at that time did not make uſe of any means to deliver his People; for it is plain there were Temporal Deliverers; there were <hi>Moſes</hi>'s, <hi>Gideon</hi>'s, <hi>David</hi>'s; but foraſmuch as theſe were only Inſtruments in the hand of God, they lifted up their eyes to the firſt Cauſe of their Deliverances; and therefore ſaid to God, Thou alone art my Truſt, and my Rock. If our Lord Jeſus had only been a ſecond Cauſe in the Work of our Redemption, had he been no more than a Creature ſent to ſave us, we need not make any difficulty to ſay, There would have been no more ado about him, than about thoſe Deliverers of old; neither would the Name of our Saviour ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear every where with that Divine Magnificence, as it doth in the Goſpel. Why, how is it that the Goſpel Honours Chriſt neither more nor leſs than God was honour'd under the Old Law? Chriſt is the Hope of the New <hi>Iſrael.</hi> See what the Apoſtle ſaith in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.12.</note> 
               <hi>There ſhall be a root of Jeſſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and in him ſhall the Gentiles truſt.</hi> He is therefore the Hope and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> he is the Hope of all Chriſtians. <hi>If in this life only we have hope in Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.19. 1 Tim. 1.1.</note> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, we are of all men moſt miſerable.</hi> Chriſt is called our Hope. <hi>Paul an Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt by the commandment of God our Saviour, and of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, our Hope:</hi> So St. <hi>Paul</hi> begins his Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy.</hi> Elſewhere Chriſt is called <hi>the hope of Glory,</hi> or the glorious Hope. Let us add to this,<note place="margin">Col. 1.27.</note> all thoſe paſſages which enjoyn us to place our Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and all thoſe that forbid us to put our confidence in the Creature, and we ſhall have a demonſtration capable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us, That our Lord and Saviour is God Bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <p>Why is all this honour put upon him? Why, becauſe he is God; we have no other reaſon, there can be no other reaſon for it. We Sacrifice to him becauſe he is God; we put our confidence in him becauſe he is God. This reaſon is contained in the words of St. <hi>Paul, Wherefore God hath given him a name above every name.</hi> That is as much as to ſay,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.9.</note> becauſe Jeſus Chriſt is God, and becauſe he hath <hi>emptied himſelf</hi> for this complicated Cauſe, <hi>a name above every name</hi> hath been given unto him. We muſt refer theſe words,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55198:28"/>
               <hi>wherefore,</hi> or <hi>for this Cauſe,</hi> to all that went before: <hi>Chriſt being in the form of God, thought it no robbery to be equal with God: neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he emptied himſelf: Wherefore &amp;c.</hi> That is to ſay, becauſe he was equal with God, and becauſe in his Incarnation he was willing to make himſelf equal with man; for this double Cauſe a Name hath been given him above every Name. Let us take heed of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, that all the Glory of Chriſt is the fruit of his Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; before ever he was made Man he had his Glory; <hi>Now,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 17.5.</note> 
               <hi>O Father, gloriſie me with the glory which I had with thee before the world was.</hi> Chriſt was God from the Beginning; <hi>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 1.1.</note> He was God, therefore, before ever <hi>he emptied himſelf,</hi> and as ſuch,<note place="margin">John 1.14.</note> he had his Glory, <hi>the glory as of the only begotten of the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, there is a Glory which he began firſt fully to enjoy after his <hi>emptying of himſelf;</hi> this is the Glory of the Mediator; a Glory which he entred upon at the time of his Incarnation, and which ſhall end on that Solemn day, when he ſhall deliver up the Kingdom to his Father. This Tranſient Glory is owing to Jeſus Chriſt's <hi>emptying of himſelf,</hi> conſidered as the Abaſement of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. The Glory of this Mediator is too great to be deriv'd to any mere Creature. He was God, and he became Man; for this double Cauſe a <hi>Name is given him above every name.</hi> It is not only becauſe he is God, nor only becauſe he was Man: Join them both together, 'tis becauſe being God, he was made Man, that he is thus highly Elevated. The Godhead is the ſpring of this Merit, the Humanity is the way of it. If he had not been God, he would not have been great enough to be our Mediator with God; and had he not been Man, he would not have been low enough to be a Mediator with regard to men: Had he been nothing but God, he would not have been known, he would have had no Name; this is the Reaſon: He being the Second Perſon in the Trinity, the Father, who had reſerved to himſelf the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the world, would have enjoyed the Worſhip of men, and the Word would have been Adored only in a hidden and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit manner. It was agreed therefore between the Father and the Son, that the Son ſhould come down to Redeem men, and that in conſideration thereof, he ſhould openly enjoy their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. This was executed accordingly, Chriſt united to himſelf a Victim, which he hath given up for us unto Death. He muſt therefore in virtue of this Treaty, receive a Name, and together
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55198:29"/>with that Name, the Adorations of Mankind. Refer we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Worſhip radically to the Divine Nature, which alone de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves Adoration; and by way of inſtrument, to the Victim, which the Word hath honoured by his Incarnation. <hi>Wherefore he hath alſo given to our Lord a name above every name, that at the name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> in theſe words, alludes to that paſſage of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 45.23.</note> where God ſaith, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto me every knee ſhall bow, and every tongue ſhall ſwear.</hi> It is obſervable alſo, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes uſe of theſe ſame words in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> to prove that we muſt all appear before the Tribunal of Chriſt: <hi>For it is written,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.11.</note> 
               <hi>as I live, ſaith the Lord, every knee ſhall bow to me, and every tongue ſhall confeſs to God.</hi> Chriſt therefore is that Lord, who in the Old Teſtament Swears that all ſhall humble themſelves before him. This is the concluſion, that every man will infer from hence, who believes that St. <hi>Paul</hi> underſtood the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> It is time to draw to a Concluſion after having ſhewed very clearly, That ſeeing Chriſt bears the Names of God; ſeeing he poſſeſſeth the Eſſence, or the Attributes of God, and that he enjoys the Worſhip that is due to none but God, he could not think it any Robbery to make himſelf Equal with God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Diſcourſe with Four Reflections, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance whereof is ſuch as may well challenge a moment more of your attention: The firſt Reflection is, That by denying the Truth we have been here confirming, we make of the Bible the ſtrangeſt Book in the world. We believe, and we have great reaſon to believe, that never was any thing ſo excellent ſeen by men. It is a work by which all Parties maintain themſelves, and throughout the whole of which we ſee nothing elſe but tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the moſt profound Wiſdom. Both the Teſtaments corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond with the moſt exacteſt Symmetry; the Old is made for the New, and the New for the Old. All the deſigns of the Holy Ghoſt agree together, neither is any thing of contradiction to be found in them. But we ſhall not find this to be ſo in the caſe of the Hypotheſis we here oppoſe. For that ſuppoſed, this Sacred Book appears a quite other thing. The Old Teſtament hath ſcarcely the leaſt correſpondence with the New: We find nothing but thwartings and contradictions between them, and it cannot in the leaſt ſeem ſtrange to me, that thoſe who embrace this Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are ſo near neighbours to Irreligion. The Old Teſtament com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55198:29"/>us in expreſs terms to Worſhip nothing but God, that we muſt put our confidence in none but God, that we are not to Hope but in God. Let us not cavil about words, I mean the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign God who hath Created Heaven and Earth: The New Teſtament, if Jeſus Chriſt be not God, overturns all this. This ſuppoſed, 'tis evident that our Saviour came not to fulfil the Law and the Prophets, but utterly to confound and deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>Let us ſpeak only of the New Teſtament. Bleſs me! what a Book ſhall we have of it, if Jeſus Chriſt be not God? 'Twill be nothing elſe but a medly of Contradictions, Snares and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. On one hand we find in it many Paſſages wherein Idolatry is condemn'd, and elſewhere as many where it is commanded: Theſe are the contradictions. We meet with Paſſages every where that invite us to Adore the Lord Jeſus, theſe are the Snares, and terrible ones too. Divine Providence took care to hide the Body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> leſt it ſhould have been made an object of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. But the Providence of the New Teſtament will be very different, it makes us every moment to meet with Chriſt under ſtrong appearances that ſolicite our Adorations, without ever cautioning us with a <hi>ſee thou do it not, worſhip God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 22 9.</note> The New Teſtament is full of Ancient Oracles pronounced to the honor of the Living God; it is clear as the Sun at Noon-day, that the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications the Apoſtles make of them, are mere childiſh Triflings and Blaſphemies, if our Saviour by one of his Natures be not that Living God whom the Prophets worſhipp'd. But then grant but the Divinity of our Lord, and all thoſe fogs and dark clouds are diſſipated; and you will meet throughout the whole New Teſtament neither contradiction, nor Snare, nor Blaſphemy. The Holy Ghoſt is always firm and unalterable in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his deſigns; he propoſeth Jeſus as the Object of Human Worſhip, becauſe he is God; this ſolves the Contradictions, this turns the pretended Snares into Arguments of Piety; this changeth the Blaſphemies into juſt and due applications of the Ancient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical paſſages.</p>
            <p>Were it not ſo, the Holy Ghoſt would have taken a quite diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent method to inſtruct us; it would have been ſo far from lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us on the brinks of the Precipice, it would have kept us at the fartheſt diſtance from it; in a thouſand paſſages it would have ſaid to us, Take heed of taking Jeſus Chriſt to be God. But why, ſay they, ſhould not the Holy Ghoſt ſpeak magnificently of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55198:30"/>that Redeemer, to whom we are ſo vaſtly obliged, and whom Providence hath raiſed to ſuch an extraordinary degree of Glory? For that very reaſon, ſay I, the Holy Ghoſt ought to ſpeak with more reſervedneſs of the Glory of Chriſt. The greater he is, the more danger of his being taken for a God. His very greatneſs makes us ſtand the more in need of Preſervatives. The Bleſſed Virgin is without doubt the moſt Glorious of all Women. What hath the Holy Ghoſt done, to prevent others from adoring her? He hath to this end ſcarcely mentioned her in the Goſpel. Set but aſide the Hiſtory of the Birth of our Saviour, where this glorious Virgin makes a neceſſary Perſonage, we meet with her no more, except it be on ſome few occaſions, where commonly ſhe appears with ſome Circumſtance or other, proper to check the deſire any one might have to worſhip her. In the reſt of the Scriptures, there is not a word of the Bleſſed Virgin. The <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, except what is ſaid in the Chapter, and the Epiſtles, make no mention of her at all. The reaſon of this ſilence is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent; It was neceſſary for to draw a Vail, as it were, over the Bleſſed Virgin, leſt the Chriſtians might be tempted to worſhip her. The more glorious ſhe is, the more need there is to take care to hide her. The caſe would have been the ſame with our Divine Redeemer, if he had not been God; the exceſs of our Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to him, and the Glory of his Exaltation, oblig'd the Holy Ghoſt not to ſpeak of him; or at leaſt, ſeeing it was not poſſible to Preach his Doctrine without ſpeaking of his Perſon, to make uſe of ſuch Expreſſions, as might make it evident, that he is not God. It was neceſſary in moſt expreſs terms, and on ſeveral occaſions, to tell men, This Jeſus whom you worſhip, is not God for all that. I ſay, it was of abſolute neceſſity to declare this with the greateſt clearneſs and plaineſs of Expreſſion imaginable. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof, the Holy Ghoſt propoſeth him to us as God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt Caution or Preſervative; we believe we have prov'd this to you by moſt clear and ſelf-evident places of Scripture, which tho they were doubtful, would for all that be of great force, becauſe whoſoever acknowledges the Wiſdom of the Holy Ghoſt, eaſily perceives that he would never have deliver'd any thing like it concerning the Godhead of our Saviour, if he had not been God indeed. The Equivocal Expreſſions that had a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable ſenſe, and a ſenſe contrary to his Divinity, would have been too dangerous in this Caſe. The Wiſdom of the Holy Ghoſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55198:30"/>would never have thought fit to have made a Repreſentation ſo proper to delude us; what ſhall we ſay then of ſo many places, where without any the leaſt Equivocation, we ſee the Divine Glory of Chriſt ſhining forth to us? it is not one Text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture fetch'd out of a Corner that we inſiſt upon, but there are a thouſand ſuch Paſſages ſcatter'd up and down the Bible, which both in the letter and the ſenſe of them, aſſert the Divinity of our Saviour. Neither can any thing be ſaid in this Caſe, but this, that the Holy Ghoſt was willing to deceive us; and if he hath deceived us, it is an innocent Error, and for which we ſhall not be reſponſible at the laſt day. Yea, the very Enemies of the Godhead of Chriſt leave Heaven-gate open to thoſe that believe the ſame. It cannot be denied, ſay they, but that there may be Salvation for thoſe that worſhip the Man-god. On the one hand it appears, that they adore nothing but what is adorable; for the very Enemies of Jeſus Chriſt profeſs to adore him. And on the other hand, they are ſenſible that the Doctrine of his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is ſufficiently confirmed in Scripture at leaſt, to juſtify the belief of the Orthodox. So that upon this account they do not doubt of their Salvation; why then ſhould any condemn them? If they adore nothing but what is indeed adorable, their Error will only be in Speculation. If they believe nothing but what the Holy Ghoſt makes them to believe by his way of ſpeaking con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt, conclude we this Reflection, The Holy Ghoſt neither can deceive, nor can be deceived; it will be our Glory to follow him always, for he cannot guide us but in the way of Truth.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Reflection upon the Difficulties that are made about this Myſtery, we have explained to you. There are three ſorts of Difficulties raiſed againſt this Doctrine of the Eternal Godhead of Jeſus Chriſt: Heart-difficulties, Wit-difficulties, and Scripture-difficulties. By Heart-difficulties, I underſtand that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnance we find in our ſelves to receive revealed Truths with a ready and teachable frame of Heart; this is that Temper the heart of Man hath received from the impreſſions of Sin; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever comes from Heaven is ſuſpected, tho indeed there be no other reaſon to ſuſpect it, ſave only this, becauſe it comes from Heaven. The Experience of all Ages is but too notorious a proof of this ſad Truth. The moſt certain Revelation hath been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputed, neither is there any thing ſo clear in Revelation that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55198:31"/>hath not been contradicted. To prove this, I will not expoſe to your view the profane Perſons, and Hereticks of the Ages paſt; this ſcandalous Proceſſion would only ſerve to afflict you. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſaith it; and this is ſufficient for man to contradict it, to doubt it, to deny it. It may be that conſidering the matter with more attention, we ſhall find that men put themſelves in an ill Humour againſt Revelation, becauſe they find in it thoſe Moral Precepts that do not at all comport with the corruption of their heart. They criticiſe the Doctrine, that they may have a pretence to ſhake off the Yoke of its commands; they controle the Precept to juſtify their Libertiniſm. I make no queſtion at all, but that a part of thoſe Clouds ſome Men meet with in the Myſtery of the Divinity of Chriſt, do proceed from the Vapours of a corrupt Heart. They queſtion the Glory of that God, whom they have no mind to obey. I have nothing to ſay againſt this firſt ſort of Difficulties, neither need I; ſince no body dares put them in form, why ſhould I take up time to refute them? I ſhall only ſay by way of Alluſion, <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Difficulties of the ſecond Order, are the Difficulties of Wit; they attack the Divinity of our Saviour, becauſe they do not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it; their bounded underſtanding meaſures all Truths according to the extent of its own Conceptions, and ſubjects to this Rule things that Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, nor ever came into the heart of Man. This Earth-worm will needs meaſure the Third Heaven; what extravagance can be greater? He cannot conceive how the Father, the Son and Holy Ghoſt are God, without making three Gods of them; therefore there is no ſuch thing. Would not one think, hearing a Man talk at this rate, that he had an infinite underſtanding, and that he compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended all things in the Infinity of his Conception? And yet we ſhall find that this preſuming Wit, doth not underſtand any thing perfectly, no not ſo much as the Nature of the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon things. He does not underſtand himſelf; and tho every thing be a Myſtery to him, yet he cannot away with the Myſteries of Religion.</p>
            <p>Yet this Enemy of the Myſteries of our Religion profeſſeth a Myſtery, which is at leaſt as inconceivable as any is in our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For he will make us believe, That a Creature hath been inveſted with infinite Attributes; that a Creature hath been made
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55198:31"/>God in Knowledge, Power, and Glory. Pray tell me what is a Myſtery, if this be not, and an inconceivable one too? The Creature turn'd God, and the Finite turn'd Infinite; the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible and contradictory thing in the World. Our Myſtery in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed aſſerts, That God humbled himſelf; but that this was by uniting himſelf perſonally with a Creature, which he took to himſelf amongſt Men; and yet this very Man that makes ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Difficulties againſt the Incarnation, tells us of a Man that is become God by a ſtrange kind of Metamorphoſis. Thus they reject the Truth, and inſtead thereof fill their Heads with <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maera's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The triumphant Raillery of the Prophane, is, That one is one, and one is three; and then making a ſhow of their being fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded of the Unity of God, they ſuppoſe the Divinity of our Saviour ſufficiently overthrown. Who doubts that one is one, and that one is not three; this is true, even in our Divine Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick; there are Three Perſons, three manners of Subſiſting, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt. We do not ſay, That theſe Three Perſons are but One Perſon, that would be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory; but we ſay, That theſe Three Perſons are in One Divine Eſſence; Three are not One, neither is One Three, in the ſame reſpect; there is a Trinity of Perſons, but an Unity of Nature. But you cannot conceive how Three Perſons can poſſeſs at the ſame time, the ſame individual Nature; what then? I conceive it no more than you do; but is it ſuch a ſtrange thing, that God ſhould be otherwiſe than we are, otherwiſe than all the things we ſee, otherwiſe than all that we can conceive? He hath aſſur'd me, That his Nature conſiſts in Three Perſons; I believe it with Submiſſion. This ought to be the Temper and Behaviour of our Underſtanding in the Difficulties it meets with on this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</p>
            <p>The Difficulties of the Third Order, are the Difficulties of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Men are aſham'd to propoſe their Heart-difficulties, for in ſo doing, they would expoſe their own Corruption; and nothing but a Spirit of Libertiniſm dares openly oppoſe its own Light to that of Divine Revelation. They rather ſearch for a plauſible pretence in the Revelation it ſelf; ſeveral places of Scripture are heap'd to-together to compoſe a Cloud that may hinder the Glory of the Goſpel from ſhining forth in its full Luſtre.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:55198:32"/>
            <p>At firſt thoſe Texts are hunted for, that prove Chriſt to be Man. But pray what is this to the Queſtion? Theſe Texts prove that he is Man; we ſay ſo too; yea, curſed be he that ſaith, that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is not Man. We believe that by one of his Natures he was Man, as we are; but this does not hinder him from being God by his other Nature. Man conſiſts of Body and Soul; can we prove from the Functions of his Body, that he hath no Soul? He Eats, he Drinks, he Sleeps, therefore he hath nothing elſe but a Body. This way of arguing is ridiculous; conſider this Man well, and you'll ſoon find by the operations of his Underſtanding, that he hath a Soul as well as a Body. This we might prove by the Example of all compounds. This is enough; we believe that our Lord Jeſus is a Perſon compos'd of two Natures, <hi>viz.</hi> of a Divine and Humane Nature, he is Fleſh and Blood; he hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, taſted Death, this ſhews him to be Man. He prayed, he worſhipped, he was ignorant of ſeveral things; this ſhews he was Man. But he formed the World, he created the Angels, he makes himſelf equal with his Heavenly Father, this proves him to be God. We readily admit the Paſſages of Scripture that rank him amongſt Men, neither dare we ſuppreſs thoſe where he is call'd God. To make our Doctrine to agree with the Scripture, we muſt hold him to be God-man.</p>
            <p>Our Adverſaries prove from ſeveral Texts of Scripture, that there is but one God; all this is time ſpent in vain, we are all fully perſuaded that there is but one God: Curſed be he that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits more than one God. But ſay they, you teach that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is God, and that the Son is God; we do ſo, and in doing ſo, we follow the Scripture; but you don't hear us ſay, That they are Two Gods; they are Two Perſons in one and the ſame God, but not Two Gods.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, That Jeſus Chriſt is equal with God; the Father and Son therefore, according to you, are two Beings equal in Dignity; doth not this imply a plurality of Gods, ſince two equal Gods cannot be the ſame God? This difficulty only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from hence, that they pretend to be ignorant of what we ſay upon the Myſtery of the Trinity; for ſuppoſing that the Father and the Son are only Two Perſons, or two manners of Subſiſting in one and the ſame Being, there is no room left for this Objection. The Father and the Son, theſe Two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, are neceſſarily equal, by ſuch an Equality, as does not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55198:32"/>thwart their Unity, becauſe they indiviſiby poſſeſs the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>They inſiſt further, that the Father is called the only true God; <hi>This is life eternal, that they know thee, the only true God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 17.3.</note> 
               <hi>and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent:</hi> What would they infer from hence? What, that Jeſus Chriſt is a God, but that he is a falſe God. A Chriſtian ear cannot with patience hear ſuch Blaſphemy; and yet they muſt come to this, before they can make thoſe words to be of any ſervice againſt the Divinity of Chriſt. It is clear that theſe Words contain an oppoſition; the oppoſite to true, is falſe. If the Father be called the only true God, in oppoſition to the Son, we eaſily ſee what follows. It is true, that there is an oppoſition in this place; not between the Father and the Son; but between the Father and whatſoever is falſly called God in the World. And in this ſenſe, as it is ſaid of the Father, That he is the only true God; we may alſo ſay of the Son, that he is the only true God, and ſo of the Holy Ghoſt; becauſe the Divine Nature, which is indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibly poſſeſs'd by theſe three Perſons, is indeed the only true God.</p>
            <p>What remains now that can give us the leaſt trouble? what can be reaſonably alledged againſt the Divinity of our Lord? ſhall we object, that he himſelf ſometimes ſpeaks of it with great reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedneſs. It is very true that our Saviour, with a great deal of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reſervedneſs, declared thoſe Truths that were capable of ſetting the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt him. The calling of the Gentiles may be one Inſtance for all. Sometimes he wraps this Doctrine under the Vail of Parables; ſometimes he makes an Alluſion to Hiſtories; wherein it ſeems that Grace was not ſhut up in the compaſs of one only People. Truth can have no entrance into Souls full of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which as the Light of the Day, comes after the Night is gone. What would this Truth of the Calling of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> have produc'd, if our Lord had preach'd it without any caution? It would not have been believed, and our Lord would have been put to death before his work had been done. I ſpeak as a Man. We may ſay the ſame thing of our Saviour's Godhead, which being ſuch, that the <hi>Jews</hi> could not bear the glory of it, he diſcovers it by little and little to them; he tries their hearts: after that he had found by the manner of their reception of theſe Words, <hi>I and my Father are one,</hi> that it was not ſeaſonable yet to declare this Doctrine, he ſtops there, and leads out the Thoughts of his Auditors to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, whom the Scripture calls Gods. If we mind it, our Lord
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55198:33"/>doth not fully juſtifie thereby, what he had ſaid in theſe words, <hi>I and my Father are one.</hi> For never did any of the Magiſtrates ſpeak at this rate: what is more, they never made themſelves Gods, nor equal with God: The Scripture indeed calls them Gods, but they never ſaid they were equal with God. Chriſt made himſelf God; and for the juſtification of himſelf, is contented to alledge the Example of the Magiſtrates. The Caſe is plain; our Saviour intends not to retract what he had ſaid; his Deſign only is, to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate the fury of the <hi>Jews.</hi> Neither indeed were they fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with it; they endeavour to lay hold on him, but he eſcaped out of their hands. Do we find him in this place ſaying, That he is not God? Not in the leaſt; he never ſaid any thing that came near it. Whereas indeed he ought to have ſaid it poſitively, and often, to make his Doctrine of more efficacy to the <hi>Jews.</hi> He ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well knew, that nothing was ſo offenſive to them as Blaſphemy, and that he quite loſt himſelf in their eſteem, by making himſelf God. And yet for all this, he always returns to it, and frequently offers them the ſame occaſion of offence. Pray what may be the meaning of this? has he no deſire that his Doctrine ſhould be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? no body dare ſay ſo. Why is it then that he ſo often touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſame Myſtery? It is plain as the Meridian Sun, that nothing but the force of Truth engageth him to make himſelf equal with his heavenly Father. He is not willing always to ſpeak openly, by a too free and open declaration of himſelf: for in this caſe he would either have convinced all his Auditors, or not. If we ſuppoſe the firſt, they would never have put him to death, which would have been equally contrary to the Prophecies of old, and to the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Mankind, which ſtood in need of his Death: If the latter, they would have put him to death too ſoon; he did need three or four years time, wherein to accompliſh his Work. Theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations oblige him to ſpeak ſparingly of, and in part to conceal the glory of his Divinity. On ſome occaſions we find that he wholly reſtrains himſelf; as in the 10th <hi>Chapter</hi> of St. <hi>John;</hi> in others again he utters himſelf with great liberty, as in the 5th <hi>Chapter</hi> of the ſame Goſpel. When there is nothing more for him to do, but to die, he frankly declares himſelf to be the Son of God. I think we may ſay, that he was the firſt Martyr for his own Divinity: for it is upon this Declaration of his, that the <hi>Jews</hi> unanimouſly cried out, He is guilty of Death. According to their Judgment he had uttered a horrid Blaſphemy, and by the Law deſerved that Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55198:33"/>ſhould be pronounced againſt him. How does he juſtifie himſelf of this Charge? Doth he alledge that of the Magiſtrates, or the Angels, on this occaſion? doth he ſay, That hels the Son of God, becauſe he was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, or becauſe he had received the power of doing Miracles, and of declaring the Truth? Thus underſtood, there was no Blaſphemy in the Caſe; and he ought, if he had not been God, to have ſet the <hi>Jews</hi> right, by juſtifying himſelf in this manner. But on the contrary, he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to the laſt moments of his Life, himſelf to be the Son of God, in a ſenſe which the <hi>Jews</hi> judged Blaſphemy; that is to ſay, The Eternal Son of God; for otherwiſe taken, it could not be Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only propound the two other Reflections, tho indeed they be no leſs important than the former. My Third Reflection is, That the Doctrine I have here aſſerted and proved, is the Doctrine of the Primitive Church. This is ſo inconteſtably true, that <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> himſelf owns, That from the firſt beginning of the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socin.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>3.</hi> ad Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec. Ab ipſo ferme naſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Eccleſiae initio, tot Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros non minus Pietate quam Doctrinâ clariſſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, tot Chriſti Sanctiſſimos Martyres, ad eout nullus ſit numerus, eum alioqui groviſſimum errorem ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> furſſe, quod Chriſtus ſit unus ille Deus qui omnia creavit, aut certe exillius ſubſtantia propria genitus.</note> there have been a great number of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men, Saints and Martyrs, who believed that Jeſus Chriſt was that God who created all things; or that he was begotten of his own Subſtance. This expreſs Acknowledgment from an Adverſary, whoſe great intereſt it was to rid himſelf of the weight Antiquity would bear againſt him, may very well paſs for a ſtrong Argument, on an occaſion where it doth not ſeem ſo proper to enter upon the Hiſtorical proof of it. It hath already been ſhewed, that the Primitive Church did believe the Eternal Divinity of our Saviour, at a time when the Church was yet in an Age of Innocence; or to make uſe of an Expreſſion of one of the Ancients, When ſhe was yet a Virgin; in a time when the Saints confirmed their Preaching by Miracles; in a time when Truth was ratified by the Seal of Martyrdom; in a time when the Voice of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had but newly ceaſed from ſounding in the Ears of the Members of it. What therefore we take from a time ſo happily circumſtanced, muſt needs be of good alloy: And may my Soul, ſay I, be with thoſe Saints and thoſe Martyrs who taught what they had but newly received from the Mouths of the Apoſtles themſelves.</p>
            <p>Is it poſſible that a ſincere Chriſtian heart ſhould find any reliſh in the oppoſite Error, which hath the concurring Teſtimony of the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:55198:34"/>Firſt Centuries againſt it, and which never got into any Credit, till after the Primitive Zeal being grown cold, and Miracles cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, men began to be left to themſelves. I confeſs I have but an ill Opinion of a Doctrine which is ſupported by no other Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. There we may find glittering Notions, and ingenious Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of the Scripture, which may be apt to take with Minds that affect Novelties. But when we conſider that the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a Revelation tranſmitted by the Miniſtry of the Apoſtles of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, we ſhall make no Difficulty to take their ſenſe from an Age that we cannot ſuſpect; and we ſhall have very mean thoughts of thoſe Innovators that have confidence enough to ſay, as one of them doth, The Firſt <hi>Chapter</hi> of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of St. <hi>John</hi> was never well explain'd till I undertook it.</p>
            <p>My laſt Reflection is concerning the ſmall concern theſe Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators have for the Peace of the Church. They would fain have us believe them to be the Diſciples of Charity; and to hear them talk, it ſhould ſeem that this Virtue is no where to be found but amongſt them. I will not now enter into an enquiry, whether under this plauſible appearance they do not deſign more ſurely to introduce their Errors; and whether after having made them ride Triumphant in the world, they would not become, inſtead of the innocent Lambs they ſeem now to be, the moſt furious Perſecutors of the Church. To know what Judgment we ought to paſs in this caſe, we need only to call to mind the Cruelty of <hi>Arius</hi> his diſciples. But l' ſtop ſhort here, and am willing to believe that our Innovators that talk ſo much of Charity and Concord, cheriſh nothing of this Spirit of Perſecution. However they muſt confeſs, that they are none of the beſt practiſers of Charity; they know very well that they cannot endeavour the Propagation of their Opinions, without troubling the Peace of mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and without ſetting Chriſtians together by the Ears. There is no need of any deeep conſideration, to perſwade our ſelves that theſe are the natural conſequences of the endeavours that would be employed to deprive the Chriſtians of a Doctrine they have been poſſeſſed of above theſe Sixteen Centuries. Why therefore ſhould the Enemies of this Doctrine ſet themſelves to be the cauſe of ſo much diſorder? There is but one only thing that could Authoriſe this their pretended Charity, <hi>viz.</hi> If the Doctrine which we Teach and Believe were inconſiſtent with Salvation. I muſt own that when we ſee a great multitude of Chriſtians in danger of incurring
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:55198:34"/>Damnation, we have good reaſon to ſay, That it is much better to expoſe them to Temporal Dangers, by propounding the Truth to them, than to ſuffer ſo many Souls to periſh by a Criminal Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. What them, is it this conſideration that animates and puſheth on our Innovators? Not in the leaſt; they dare not ſay they are in fear for our Salvation, whilſt at the ſame time they ſet Heaven Gates wide open to all ſorts of Hereticks, to Mahometans and Heathens: They, I ſay, who hide themſelves in the Society of other Chriſtians, and deſire nothing ſo earneſtly as to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their Communion: They own us to be in a ſtate of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and declare that we have retained all the Fundamental and Saving Points of Chriſtianity. Where is therefore the Charity of theſe raſh Perſons in undertaking to ſhake a Doctrine, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be attack'd with any ſucceſs, without filling the Conſciences of men with Trouble, and without ſhedding whole torrents of Chriſtian Blood? ſuch a deſign as this, cannot be the effect of any thing but Pride. In a word; Men have a mind to diſtinguiſh themſelves by the novelty of their Opinions, and to raiſe their own Glory by abaſing that of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Theſe who deſtroy the Temple of God, God will deſtroy.</hi> I tell you, that more than the Temple is here. <hi>Entreat we our dear Lord Jeſus, that it may pleaſe him to enlighten his Enemies, and confirm us more and more in the belief of his Divinity. To him, even as to the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, be Humour and Glory for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:55198:35"/>
            <head>A Declaration of the Opinion of the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters who are now Refugees in <hi>England,</hi> about ſome Points of Religion, in Oppoſition to the <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE under written, the Refugees, <hi>French</hi> Miniſters in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> having underſtood by a Letter which my Lord the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> who at preſent is in <hi>Holland,</hi> hath writ to Monſieur <hi>le Coq</hi> Counſellor in the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> and an Illuſtrious Confeſſor of the Truth, the ſtrange Reports that have been ſpread, as if we were not ſound in the Faith, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly with relation to the Doctrine of the Holy <hi>Trinity,</hi> and Grace, and the need there is to diſſipate the ſame; and being moreover perſwaded that by this Explication of our Belief, we ſhall perform a thing that will ſerve for the Edification and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of our Brethren, and will have its fruit, if the Lord pleaſe, eſpecially in the Land of our Nativity, after ſome Amicable and Brotherly Conferences we have had upon this matter, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Monſieur <hi>le Coq;</hi> we have all of us agreed to declare, as we do in the Sincerity of our Hearts:</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. That we Believe the whole Scripture Divinely Inſpir'd, ſo that all Men are obliged to receive every thing therein Revealed, with an entire Submiſſion of Faith.</item>
               <item>II. That we receive with Reverence and Submiſſion whatſoever the Scripture teacheth concerning the <hi>Nature of God,</hi> and his <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes,</hi> of his <hi>Spirituality, Infiniteneſs, Incomprehenſibility, Preſcience</hi> even of <hi>Future Contingencies,</hi> and of all others the ſaid Scripture at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes to him.</item>
               <item>III. That we Believe alſo what it delivers concerning the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Perſons</hi> in one only <hi>Divine Eſſence,</hi> and concerning the <hi>Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Son,</hi> according as the ſaid Articles are ſet down in the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55198:35"/>VI. XIV. and XV. of the Confeſſion of Faith of the Reformed Churches of <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IV. That we hold alſo as an Article of our Faith, That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt by dying on the Croſs,</hi> hath not only left us an Example that we ſhould follow his Footſteps; but moreover, that his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Deſign therein, was to ſatisfie the Divine Juſtice for us, in bearing the Puniſhment of our Sins, as he actually did.</item>
               <item>V. That we deteſt the Opinions of <hi>Socinus,</hi> and of all others that are contrary to the foremention'd Truths; not conſidering them as Innocent Opinions, or Tolerable Errors, but as Hereſies which abſolutely overturn the Foundations of the Chriſtian Faith; and that conſequently we can have no Religious Communion with thoſe that follow them, or teach them.</item>
               <item>VI. That we do alſo condemn their Opinion, who deny the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and immediate Operation of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> in the Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Man to God; and who pretend that the Holy Ghoſt doth not ſo open the Hearts, as to make Men believe the Word, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline them to love God, and to obey his Commandments.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And that for the reſt, we heartily Subſcribe to the Confeſſion of Faith of the Reformed Churches of <hi>France,</hi> which thoſe of us who have been admitted to the Holy Miniſtry in that Kingdom, have already Subſcribed, without pretending to meddle with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>We truſt that God will give us his Grace to preſerve this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine pure and entire to our laſt Breath, and to evidence it as well in our publick Sermons, as our private Converſations.</p>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>London</hi> the 30th. of <hi>March</hi> 1691.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>T. Satur,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Montauban,</hi> Moderator.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A. Piozet,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Mans,</hi> Joint-Moderator.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>C. G. La Mothe,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Rouan,</hi> Secretary.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Du Bourdieu,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Montpelier.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Le Chenevix,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Mante.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>P. Charles,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Mauveſin.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:55198:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:55198:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:55198:37"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>L. Rival,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Salies.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>O. Champion,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Mougon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bejamin de Daillón,</hi> formerly Paſtor of the Church of <hi>Rochefou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cault.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sers,</hi> formerly Miniſter in the Church of <hi>Montredon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>La Caux,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Caſtres.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>De Guilhem,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Brebyeres</hi> in <hi>Peregord.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. Lovis Malide,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Caſteljaloux.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>De Primeroſe,</hi> Miniſter of the <hi>French</hi> Church of <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mitault,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Chef Boutonne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Samuel Metayer,</hi> Miniſter of St. <hi>Quentin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>De Joux,</hi> formerly Paſtor of the Reformed Church of <hi>Lyon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>P. Teſtas,</hi> formerly Miniſter of the Reformed Church of <hi>Milhan</hi> in <hi>Guienne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marc Vernoux,</hi> formerly Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Mazemet</hi> in <hi>Languedoc.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fauleon,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Fecamp</hi> in <hi>Normandy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Betoule,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Duras.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. Campredon,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Pont de Larn.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pierry Fleury,</hi> formerly Miniſter of the Church of St. <hi>Aignan</hi> upon the <hi>Maine</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean Farcy,</hi> Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Mouchamp</hi> in <hi>Low Poictou.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jacques Severin,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Chery les Roſois</hi> in <hi>Ferache.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>F. Teſtas,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Poitiers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jacques Tirel,</hi> formerly Miniſter at St. <hi>Vaaſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Canolle,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Gontauld.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pont,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Mazeres.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean Gommare,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Muffidan</hi> in the Dutchy of <hi>La Force.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baignoux,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Poitiers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>David Grimaudet,</hi> formerly Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Deſaigns.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jacques Doulés,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Angles.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pierre Fontaine,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Royan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Daniel du Tens,</hi> formerly Miniſter of the Reformed Church of <hi>Angers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. Solinhac,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Realville.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pierre Souchet,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Rochouard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jacob de Rouffignac,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Puycaſque.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. Bardon,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Bruniquel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean Baron,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Mazemet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean Molles,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Cardalhac.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:55198:37"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Daniel Chais la Place,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ave</hi> in <hi>Dauphiné.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Le Sauvage,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Alenſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean Cabibel,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Braſſac.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Etienne Molenér,</hi> formerly Miniſter <hi>de Liſle</hi> in <hi>Jordain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philippa la Loe,</hi> formerly Miniſter at. <hi>Orbec.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean Couyer,</hi> formerly Paſtor of <hi>Linieres</hi> in <hi>Angoumors.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jacob Aſſelin,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Dieppe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean Forent,</hi> formerly Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Syon</hi> in <hi>Bré<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagné.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>C. Pegorier,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Havre.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charles Bertheau,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>P. Rouſſillion,</hi> formerly Miniſter of the Baronny of <hi>Montreden</hi> in the <hi>Lower Languedoe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>P. Pezé Dégalimére,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Mans.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barthelemy Balaguier,</hi> formerly of the Church of <hi>Aiguefonde</hi> in the <hi>High Languedoc.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paul Graviſſet,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Ardenay</hi> in the Countrey of <hi>Maine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean Boudet,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Genebrieres.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Joſeph de la Mothe,</hi> formerly Miniſter of the Reformed Church of <hi>Puymirol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jouneau,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Barbeſieux.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. Lions,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Montelimart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gabriel Barbier,</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Greenwich.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pierre Blanc,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rival,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. Lombard,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Angers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. Majou,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Ciré.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Durand Raoux,</hi> formerly Miniſter of St. <hi>Privat.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. Graveral,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Lyons.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jacques Laborie,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barthelemy Baſſet,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. M. Verchiere,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Abraham Gilbert,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Melle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean Charpentier,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charles Contet,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Antoine Review,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>H. de Rocheblave,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean le Febvre,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A. Lombard,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:55198:38"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean Bernard,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eliſee Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auld,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brocus de Hande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ens,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Caſteljaloux.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mote,</hi> formerly Miniſter of the Place <hi>de Barre</hi> in <hi>Cevenes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jacques Miſſon,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Niort.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pierre Boſſatran,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Niort</hi> in <hi>Poitou.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Michel David,</hi> formerly Miniſter of my Lady Dutcheſs <hi>de la Force.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pierre Ticier,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Mauveſin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean la Motthe,</hi> Miniſter of the Church of <hi>la Baſtide Rouairouſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Michel Cordier,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Fieux.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bertheau</hi> the Elder, Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Montpelier.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>La Riviere,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Toulouſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brevet,</hi> formerly Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Dompierre</hi> and <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuf.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A. Fornes,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A. Richard,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Eſperauſſes</hi> in <hi>Languedoc.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>P. Aſtruc,</hi> Miniſter of the Church of <hi>la Gazelle</hi> in <hi>Auvergne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jean Chabbert,</hi> Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>La Porte,</hi> formerly Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Agen</hi> in <hi>Low Guienne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. Dejoux</hi> Junior, Chaplain in Their Majeſties Ship the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A. de</hi> St. <hi>Denys,</hi> formerly Miniſter at <hi>Sancourt</hi> in <hi>Normandy.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
